<resources>

    <string name="menu_open">Open</string>
    <string name="menu_close">Close</string>
    <string name="menu_home">Home</string>
    <string name="menu_language">Language</string>
    <string name="menu_search">Search</string>
    <string name="menu_settings">Settings</string>
    <string name="menu_history">History</string>
    <string name="menu_share">Share</string>


    <string name="app_name">Seera Itoophiyaa</string>
    <string-array name="c1">
        <item>ርዕስ I: አካላዊ ሰዎች</item>
        <item>ርዕስ II: የሰዎች አቅም </item>
        <item>ርዕስ III: አካላት ኮርፖሬት እና ንብረት ከተወሰነ መድረሻ ጋር </item>
        <item>ርዕስ IV: በግንኙነት ትስስር እና በወዳጅነት</item>
        <item>ርዕስ V: ስኬቶች</item>
        <item>ርዕስ VI:በአጠቃላይ እቃዎች እና ይዞታ</item>
        <item>ርዕስ VII:የግለሰብ ባለቤትነት</item>
        <item>ርዕስ VIII: የግል ባለቤትነት</item>
        <item>ርዕስ IX ኮርፖሬት ባለቤትነት፣ ተጠቃሚነት እና ሌሎች በ RAM ውስጥ ያሉ መብቶች</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="detailsc1">
        <item>የሲቪል ኮድ:> አካላዊ ሰዎች::
የግዛታችን የሕግ ሥርዓት በትክክል እንዲዳብር አስፈላጊ ሆኖ ሲገኝ የፍትሐ ብሔር ሕግ ማውጣት አስፈላጊ ሆኖ ሳለ; እና
የፍትሐ ብሔር ሕጉ በእኛ ቁጥጥር ሥር ተዘጋጅቶ የኛን የሴኔት እና የተወካዮች ምክር ቤት ፈቃድ ያገኘ ቢሆንም፣
ስለዚህ በተሻሻለው ሕገ መንግሥታችን አንቀፅ 34 እና 88 መሠረት የሴኔታችን እና የተወካዮች ምክር ቤት ውሳኔዎችን አፅድቀናል፣ የሴኔትና የተወካዮች ምክር ቤቶችን ውሳኔዎች አፅድቀን እንደሚከተለው እንገልፃለን።
1. ይህ ህግ "የፍትሐ ብሔር ህግ 1960" ተብሎ ሊጠቀስ ይችላል.
2. የ 1960 የፍትሐ ብሔር ሕግ, በ 1960 እንደ ልዩ ጉዳይ ቁጥር 2 በተለየ ጥራዝ የታተመ.
በአዲስ አበባ ግንቦት 5 ቀን 1960 ተከሰተ
ጻሓፈ ታእዛዝ ኣክሊሉ ሃብተ ወልድ
ምክትል ጠቅላይ ሚኒስትር እና ሚኒስትር ፔን </item>
        <item>ርዕስ II ሰብአዊ መብቶች
ምዕራፍ 1. አጠቃላይ መርሆዎች
ስነ ጥበብ. 192.- የአቅም ህግ.

ማንኛውም አካላዊ ሰው በህጋዊ መንገድ አቅም እንደሌለው እስካልተገለጸ ድረስ ሁሉንም የሲቪል ህይወት ተግባራትን ማከናወን ይችላል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 193.- አጠቃላይ የአካል ጉዳት.

አጠቃላይ የአካል ጉዳተኞች በእድሜ ወይም በአእምሮ ሁኔታ ወይም በእነሱ ላይ በተጣለባቸው ጥፋቶች ላይ የተመሰረቱ ናቸው.

ስነ ጥበብ. 194.- ልዩ የአካል ጉዳተኞች.

(፩) በሰዎች ዜግነት ወይም በሥራቸው ምክንያት ልዩ የአካል ጉዳተኞች ሊቀርቡ ይችላሉ።
(2) በዚህ ርዕስ ምዕራፍ 5 (ክፍል 389-393) እና ልዩ ደንቦች.

ስነ ጥበብ. 195.- የዘፈቀደ ገደቦች.

(፩) ማንም ሰው የዜግነት መብቱን በከፊልም ቢሆን ከመጠቀም ወይም ከመጠቀም መቆጠብ አይችልም።
(፪) እነዚህን መብቶች ለመጠቀም ወይም ለመጠቀም በፈቃድ የሚደረጉ ማናቸውም ገደቦች በሕጋዊ ጥቅም ካልተረጋገጠ በቀር ውጤት የለውም።

ስነ ጥበብ. 196.- የአካል ጉዳት ማስረጃ.

(1) አቅም ይገመታል።
(፪) የአካል ጉዳተኛ ነኝ የሚል ሰው ሁሉ የአካል ጉዳተኛ መሆኑን ማረጋገጥ አለበት።

ስነ ጥበብ. 197.- ቋሚ ቦታ የኮርፖሬት አካላት እና ንብረቶች.

የኮርፖሬት አካላት እና የመገኛ ቦታ-ተኮር ንብረቶች በባህሪያቸው ከነሱ ጋር የተያያዙትን ድንጋጌዎች የማሟላት አቅም</item>
        <item>ርዕስ III. የተለያዩ ቦታዎች ያሏቸው ኩባንያዎች እና ንብረቶች
ምዕራፍ 1. የአስተዳደር አካላት እና ቤተክርስቲያን
ስነ ጥበብ. 394.- መንግሥት.

(፩) መንግሥት እንደ ሰው በሕጋዊ መንገድ ይያዛል።
(፪) እንዲሁም ከባሕርይው ጋር የሚስማማውን ሁሉንም መብቶች በአካሎቻቸው ሊይዝና ሊጠቀምበት ይችላል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 395.- የክልል ግዛቶች መከፋፈል.

(፩) ተክላይ ጉዕዛት፣ አውራጃ ጉዕዛታ፣ ወረዳና መቅተል-ወረዳ ጉዛቶች እና የከተማና ገጠር ማኅበረሰቦች መብት የማግኘት መብት አሇባቸው።
(፪) ስለሆነም በየአካሎቻቸው አማካይነት በአስተዳደር ሕግ የተሰጣቸውን መብቶች ሁሉ ሊያገኙና ሊጠቀሙባቸው ይችላሉ።
             ስነ ጥበብ. 396.- ሚኒስትሮች.

(፩) የኢትዮጵያ መንግሥት ሚኒስትሮች መብት አላቸው።
(፪) ስለሆነም በየአካሎቻቸው አማካይነት በአስተዳደር ሕግ የተሰጣቸውን መብቶች ሁሉ ሊያገኙና ሊጠቀሙባቸው ይችላሉ።

ስነ ጥበብ. 397.- የህዝብ አስተዳደር ባለስልጣናት እና ተቋማት.

ሁሉም የመንግስት አስተዳደር ባለስልጣናት፣ መስሪያ ቤቶች ወይም ተቋማት በአስተዳደር ህግ ስብዕና የተሰጣቸው እንደ ሙያው፣ የመብት ተገዢዎች ናቸው።

ስነ ጥበብ. 398.- የኢትዮጵያ ኦርቶዶክስ ተዋሕዶ ቤተ ክርስቲያን።

(፩) የኢትዮጵያ ኦርቶዶክስ ተዋሕዶ ቤተ ክርስቲያን በሕግ እንደ አንድ ሰው ተቆጥራለች።
(፪) ስለሆነም በአስተዳደር ሕጎች የተሰጡትን መብቶች በሙሉ በአካሎቻቸው አማካይነት ሊጠቀምባቸው ይችላል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 399.- አብያተ ክርስቲያናት, አድባራት እና ገዳማት.

የኢትዮጵያ ኦርቶዶክስ ተዋሕዶ ቤተ ክርስቲያን አካል የሆኑ አብያተ ክርስቲያናት፣ አድባራትና ገዳማት እንደ ሙያ ሁሉ በአስተዳደር ሕግ በሚወስኑት ቅድመ ሁኔታዎችና ወሰኖች መብት አላቸው።
         ስነ ጥበብ. 400.- ኃይሎች እና አካላት.

(፩) ከዚህ በላይ ባለው ቁጥር የተመለከቱት የአካላት ሥልጣንና እነዚህን አካላት ለመወከል የተፈቀዱ አካላት ሥልጣን በአስተዳደር ሕግ የተደነገገ ነው።
(፪) አንዳንድ መብቶችን ለመጠቀም አንዳንድ ሁኔታዎችን ወይም ሥርዓቶችን እንዲጠብቁ በእነዚህ አካላት ላይ ሊያስገድዱ ይችላሉ።

ስነ ጥበብ. 401.- በሕግ የተደነገጉ መስፈርቶችን ማሟላት አለመቻል.

(፩) በዚህ ምዕራፍ የተመለከቱት አካላት በሕግ የተሰጣቸውን መደበኛ ሁኔታዎች ሳይፈጽሙ በሕግ ከተሰጣቸው ሥልጣን የሚበልጡ ድርጊቶች ምንም ውጤት አይኖራቸውም።
(፪) የንኡስ ቁጥር ድንጋጌዎች። (፩) በሕግ ግልጽ ባይሆንም በነዚህ ጉዳዮች ላይ ተፈጻሚ ይሆናል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 402. - ውድቅ መሆን.

(1) ሰከንድ. 401 ማንኛውም ፍላጎት ያለው አካል ሊጠራ ይችላል.
(፪) ድርጊቱ ከተፈፀመበት ቀን አንሥቶ ዐሥር ዓመታት ካለፉ በኋላ መጥራት አይቻልም።

ስነ ጥበብ. 403.- ከውል ውጪ ተጠያቂነት።

(1) በዚህ ምዕራፍ ውስጥ የተገለጹት አካላት በዚህ ኮድ ርዕስ "ከውል ውጭ የሆነ ተጠያቂነት እና ህገ-ወጥ ማበልጸግ" (ሰከንድ 2027-2161) በተደነገገው መሰረት ይገለፃሉ.
(2) በተዛማጅ ርዕስ (ክፍል, 2162-2178) በተደነገገው መሠረት የተገኘውን ማንኛውንም ሕገ-ወጥ ማበልጸጊያ ይክፈሉ.</item>
        <item>ርዕስ V. ይቀጥላል
የእረፍት ጊዜ. 1. ተተኪ ለውጦች
አንቀጽ 1. አጠቃላይ ድንጋጌዎች
አንቀፅ 1.- የተከታታዩ መከፈት እና ተከታታይ እቃዎች መፈጠር

ስነ ጥበብ. 826.- ተከታታይ መክፈቻ.
(፩) አንድ ሰው የሞተ እንደሆነ፤ ሟች የተባለው ሰው ውርስ የሚከፈተው በሞተበት ጊዜ በዋናው መኖሪያው በነበረበት ቦታ ነው።
. . . .

ስነ ጥበብ. 827.- ኑዛዜን የሚፈጥሩ ነገሮች-1. የሕይወት ኢንሹራንስ.

(፩) ሟቹ ተካፋይ በሆነበት የሕይወት ኢንሹራንስ ውል አፈጻጸም የሚከፈለው ገንዘብ፤ ሟቹ ተጠቃሚ ለመሾም ያልቻለ እንደሆነ ወይም ኢንሹራንስ የተገባለት የሟቹ ወራሾች የውርሱ ተካፋይ ከመሆን ይልቅ ተጠቃሚው የሆነ እንደሆነ። ሌላ አመላካች.
(፪) በሌላ መልኩ የውርሱ አካል አይደሉም።
         ስነ ጥበብ. 829.- የተለያዩ ዓይነቶች ስኬት.

(፩) የሞተው ሰው ውርስ በውርስ ወይም በውርስ ሊሆን ይችላል።
(፪) ከፊል ውርስ ሊነፈገው ይችላል፤ ከፊሉ ደግሞ ውርስ ሊወገድ ይችላል።
(፫) ሟቹ በኑዛዜ ያልተቀበለው ንብረት ለሕጋዊ ወራሾቹ ነው።

አንቀጽ 2 የስኬት ችሎታ
ስነ ጥበብ. 830.- ለስኬት ሁኔታዎች.

አንድ ሰው ሟቹን ሊወክል አይችልም እሱ ወይም እሷ በሕይወት ካልተረፈ እና ለመተካት ብቁ ካልሆነ በስተቀር።

ስነ ጥበብ. 831. የሟቹ ወራሽ ህይወት.

(፩) ሟቹ በሞተበት ቀን ሰው የሚኖርበትን የሚያረጋግጥ ማስረጃ በዚህ ርዕስ ስለ “ሥጋዊ አካላት” (አንቀጽ 47-153) በተደነገገው መሠረት ነው።
(፪) መቅረት የሚያስከትለውን ውጤት በተመለከተ የዚሁ የባለቤትነት ድንጋጌዎች ተፈጻሚዎች ይሆናሉ (አንቀጽ ፻፶፬-፲፯፫)።
(፫) የውክልና ተካፋይነትን በሚመለከቱ ድንጋጌዎች በዚህ ክፍል ውስጥ ምንም ነገር አይነካም።

ስነ ጥበብ. 832. - በተመሳሳይ ጊዜ የሞቱ ሰዎች.

ሁለት ወይም ከዚያ በላይ ሰዎች ሲሞቱ እና ከእነዚህ ሰዎች መካከል የትኛው ከሌላው እንደሚተርፍ ለማወቅ የማይቻል ከሆነ የእያንዳንዳቸው ተተኪነት ከሌላው እንደሚተርፍ ማረጋገጥ አይቻልም, የእነዚህ ሰዎች ተተኪ እያንዳንዳቸው እንደ ተተኪው ይመራሉ.
            የመጨረሻው የተረፈው ግን ከሌሎቹ ተተኪዎች ማንኛውንም ነገር መቀበል</item>
        <item>ርዕስ VI አጠቃላይ እቃዎች እና እቃዎች
ምዕራፍ 1. በአጠቃላይ እቃዎች
ክፍል .1126. የተለያዩ አይነት መሳሪያዎች.
ሁሉም መሳሪያዎች ተንቀሳቃሽ ወይም ቋሚ ናቸው.

ስነ ጥበብ. 1127.- አካላዊ ንብረት.- 1. መርህ.

አካላዊ ሀብቶች አካላዊ ሕልውና ያላቸው እና ግለሰባዊ ባህሪያቸውን ሳያጡ እራሳቸውን ማንቀሳቀስ ወይም በሰዎች መንቀሳቀስ የሚችሉ ነገሮች ናቸው።

ክፍል .1128.- 2. የመያዣ ዋስትናዎች.

በሕግ ካልተደነገገ በቀር፣ በዋስትናዎች ውስጥ የተካተቱት የይገባኛል ጥያቄዎች እና ሌሎች የማይዳሰሱ መብቶች እንደ ቁሳዊ ሀብት ይቆጠራሉ።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1129. 3. የተፈጥሮ ኃይሎች.

በሕግ ካልተደነገገ በቀር፣ እንደ ኤሌትሪክ ያሉ ኢኮኖሚያዊ ጠቀሜታ ያላቸው የተፈጥሮ ኃይሎች፣ ሰው በያዘበት ቦታ ሥጋዊ ዕቃዎች ተደርገው ይወሰዳሉ።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1130.- የማይንቀሳቀሱ ነገሮች.

መሬቱ እና ህንጻዎቹ የማይንቀሳቀሱ እንደሆኑ ይቆጠራሉ.

ስነ ጥበብ. 1131.- የእቃዎች ውስጣዊ አካላት. 1. መመሪያዎች.

በሌላ መልኩ ካልተደነገገው በቀር የዕቃው መብቶች ወይም ግንኙነቶች ለሁሉም የውስጥ አካላት ተፈጻሚ ይሆናሉ።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1132.- 2. ፍቺ.

(፩) በተለምዶ የአንድ ነገር አካል ነው ተብሎ የሚታሰበው ማንኛውም ነገር እንደ ውስጣዊ አካል ይቆጠራል።
(፪) ከዕቃው ጋር በአካል የተዋሃደና ይህንኑ ነገር ሳያጠፋ ወይም ሳይጎዳ ሊነጠል የማይችል ማንኛውም ንጥረ ነገር የዕቃው ውስጣዊ አካል እንደሆነ ይቆጠራል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1133.- 3. እንጨትና ኮርፖሬሽን.

(፩) ዛፎችና ማኅበራት ከመሬት እስኪለያዩ ድረስ የሰውነት አካል መሆን አለባቸው።
(፪) ከመሬቱ ለመለያየት የሚደረጉ ውሎች ወይም መለያየትን የሚያመለክት እንደ የተለየ ሥጋዊ ዕቃ ይቈጠራሉ።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1134.- 4. የሶስተኛ ወገኖች መብቶች.

(፩) በሰውነት ውስጥ የሚንቀሳቀስ ወይም የማይንቀሳቀስ ማንኛውም ነገር የተለየ ንጥረ ነገር መፍጠር ያቆማል።
(፪) ከዚህ በፊት በሶስተኛ ወገኖች የተያዙት መብቶች በሙሉ ጠፍተዋል።
(፫) ለጉዳት ወይም ለሕገ-ወጥ መበልጸግ ተጠያቂነት ላይ ተመስርቶ ክስ ለማቅረብ የሶስተኛ ወገን መብቱን የሚነካ ምንም ነገር የለም።
    </item>
        <item>TITLE VII። የግል ባለቤትነት
ምዕራፍ 1. ማግኘት, ማስተላለፍ, ማስወገድ እና የባለቤትነት የምስክር ወረቀት
ክፍል 1. የባለቤትነት መብትን ማግኘት
አንቀጽ 1. ሥራ
ስነ ጥበብ. 1151.- መመሪያዎች.

በአካላዊ ንብረት የተያዘ ሰው ባለቤት ለመሆን በማሰብ ጌታ የሌለው ሰው የዚህን ንብረት ባለቤትነት ይይዛል.

ስነ ጥበብ. 1152.- እንስሳት.

(፩) የሠለጠኑ ወይም የተማረኩ እንስሶች ከባለቤታቸው ቁጥጥር አምልጠው በሚቀጥለው ወር ውስጥ መልሰው ለመያዝ ያልሞከሩ ወይም ለአንድ ወር ያህል ለመያዝ መሞከራቸውን ያቆሙ እንስሳት ባለቤት አልባ ይሆናሉ።
(፪) በንኡስ ቁጥር (፩) የተመለከተው ድንጋጌ በፈረስ ወይም በአሲኒን ዝርያ ወይም በመራቢያቸው ላይ ወይም በግመሎችና በከብት እንስሳት ላይ ተፈጻሚ አይሆንም።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1153.- የከብት እርባታ.

(፩) ቀፎአቸውን የለቀቁ የንቦች መንጋ ጌታ እንደሌላቸው ይቆጠራል።
(፪) በቀፎው የሰፈሩበት ሰው በይዞታው ምክንያት የዚህ መንጋ ባለሀብት ይሆናል።
(፫) የቀድሞው ባለሀብት ወደ አባረራቸው ቦታ ወስዶ ወዲያውኑ ወደ መኖሪያቸው ሊደርስ ይችላል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1154.- ነገር ተገኝቷል.- 1. ተረኛ ማግኘት.

(፩) አካላዊ ነገርን ያገኘና የያዘ ሰው ያገኘውን ወይም ያገኘውን ነገር እንዲያሳውቅ የሚጠይቀውን የአስተዳደር ደንቦችን ማክበር አለበት።
(፪) እነዚህ ደንቦች በሌሉበት ጊዜ ግኝቶቹን ለማሳወቅ እና በሁኔታዎች ላይ አስፈላጊውን ምርመራ ለማድረግ አስፈላጊውን እርምጃ ሁሉ ለባለቤቱ ለማስታወቅ።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1155.- 2. የቁስ ይዞታ.

(፩) ፈላጊው የተመለከተውን ግዴታዎች አሟልቷል። 1154 በእጁ የተገኘውን ይይዛል.
(2) እንደዚህ ባሉ ሁኔታዎች ለመጠበቅ ሁሉንም ምክንያታዊ እርምጃዎችን ይውሰዱ።</item>
        <item>ርዕስ VIII የቤተ ክርስቲያን ባለቤትነት፣ ተጠቃሚነት እና ሌሎች በ RAM ውስጥ ያሉ መብቶች

ምዕራፍ 1. የጋራ ባለቤትነት
አንቀጽ 1. አጠቃላይ ድንጋጌዎች
ስነ ጥበብ. 1257.- መመሪያዎች.

(፩) አንድ ነገር በብዙ ሰዎች የጋራ ባለሀብቶች ሊሆኑ ይችላሉ።
(2) በዚህ ሕግ ርዕስ IX ውስጥ የግብርና ማኅበራትን እና የቤት ባለቤቶችን ኦፊሴላዊ ማኅበራትን የሚመለከቱ ደንቦችን የሚነካ ነገር የለም። (አንቀጽ 1489-1534)።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1258.- የጋራ ባለቤትነት እንዴት እንደሚስተካከል.

(፩) የሕጉ የግዴታ ድንጋጌዎች እንደተጠበቁ ሆነው የጋራ ባለሀብቶቹ መብትና ግዴታዎች ከጋራ ባለሀብቶቹ በሚመነጩት ዕቃዎችና የጋራ ባለሀብቶቹ በገቡት ውል ተገዢ ይሆናሉ።
(፪) በንኡስ ቁጥር የተመለከቱት ሰነዶች ወይም ስምምነቶች ከሌለ እነዚህ ድንጋጌዎች ተፈጻሚ ይሆናሉ። (፩) የተሠሩት ወይም እነዚህ ሰነዶች ወይም ውሎች ጉድለት ያለባቸው ወይም ከሕግ ጋር የሚቃረኑ ናቸው።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1259.- የፍትሃዊነት ግምት.

በእያንዳንዱ የጋራ ባለቤት የተያዙት አክሲዮኖች እኩል ናቸው ተብሎ ይታሰባል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1260.- በአክሲዮኖች ላይ መብቶች.

(፩) እያንዳንዱ የጋራ ባለሀብት ድርሻውን ለመጣል ወይም ለማስያዝ ይችላል።
(፪) የእያንዳንዱ የጋራ ባለሀብት ገንዘብ ጠያቂዎች አክሲዮኑን ማያያዝ ይችላሉ።
ስነ ጥበብ. 1261.- ቅድመ-ቅደም ተከተል ህጋዊ መብት.
(፩) የጋራ ባለሀብቶቹ የጋራ በሆነው ዕቃ የተገኘውን አክሲዮን ሦስተኛ ወገን እንዲሸጥላቸው ለማስገደድ ሕጋዊ መብት አላቸው።
(2) በንኡስ አንቀጽ 1 (1) ውስጥ ያለው መብት በዚህ ርዕስ ምዕራፍ 4 (ክፍል 1386-1409) በተደነገገው መንገድ መተግበር አለበት.

ስነ ጥበብ. 1262.- የአክሲዮን መሰጠት.

(፩) አንድ የጋራ ባለሀብት የጋራ በሆነው ዕቃ ውስጥ ያለውን ድርሻ አሳልፎ የሰጠ እንደሆነ ይህ ድርሻ ለሌሎቹ የጋራ ባለሀብቶች ይሆናል።
(፪) ድርሻውን ያስረከበ የጋራ ባለሀብት እጅ ከመሰጠቱ በፊት ለነበሩት ዕዳዎች አላፊ ይሆናል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1263. የነገር አጠቃቀም።

እያንዳንዱ የጋራ ባለሀብት በጋራ የተያዘውን ዕቃ እንደተገኘበት ዓላማ እና የሌሎቹን የጋራ ባለቤቶች መብት ግምት ውስጥ በማስገባት ሊጠቀምበት ይችላል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1664. - መጨመር.

(፩) በጋራ የተያዘ ዕቃ ፍሬ አብሮ ነው።
(፪) እያንዳንዱ የጋራ ባለሀብት እነዚህን ፍሬዎች ለመከፋፈል በማናቸውም ጊዜ ማመልከት ይችላል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1265.- በአንድነት የተያዙ ነገሮችን ማስተዳደር-1. አብላጫ ደንብ።</item>
        <item>ርዕስ X. የእውነተኛ ንብረት ተመዝጋቢዎች
ምዕራፍ 1. መዝገቦችን እና ማስታወሻዎችን መያዝ
ስነ ጥበብ. 1553.- መመሪያዎች.

የሪል እስቴት መዛግብት በእያንዳንዱ አውራጃ ጉአዛት የሪል እስቴት መዛግብት ጠባቂዎች ይጠበቃሉ።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1554.- መዝገቦችን ለመጠበቅ ቦታዎችን ማደራጀት.

(፩) የሪል እስቴት መዝገብ ሹሞችና ረዳቶቻቸው ሹመትና ደረጃ በግብርና መምሪያ በተደነገገው መሠረት ይሆናል።
(፪) ሚኒስቴሩ የሪል እስቴት መዛግብትን ለመጠበቅ የቦታዎቹን ማቴሪያል አደረጃጀት ይወስናል፤ ሥራቸውም በትክክል መፈጸሙን ያረጋግጣል።
(3) የሪል እስቴት መዛግብትን ለመጠበቅ እና ለማቆየት ተገቢውን እርምጃ ይውሰዱ።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1555.- የመሬት ክፍፍል ወረዳዎች.

(፩) መሬቱ በተከፋፈለባቸው አውራጃዎች መሠረት የሪል እስቴት መዝገብ በእያንዳነዱ ማከማቻ ውስጥ መቀመጥ አለበት።
(፪) የግብርና ሚኒስቴር መሬቱ የተከፈለባቸውን አውራጃዎች ወሰን ይወስናል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1556.- ዋና መዝገብ.

የንብረት መዛግብት እና የሞርጌጅ መዛግብት ለእያንዳንዱ የጥበቃ ቦታ እና ለእያንዳንዱ ወረዳ ይጠበቃሉ።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1557.- የሪል እስቴት ምዝገባ.

የ cadastre ሁኔታዎች እንዲህ ያለውን ሥርዓት ተቀባይነት ከሆነ, በእያንዳንዱ ወረዳ ውስጥ የማይንቀሳቀስ ንብረት መዝገብ መያዝ አለበት.

ስነ ጥበብ. 1558.- የባለቤቶች መመዝገቢያ.

የካዳስተር አካባቢ የማይንቀሳቀስ ንብረት መዝገብ እንዲዘጋጅ የማይፈቅድ ከሆነ የባለቤትነት መዝገብ በየወረዳው ይቀመጥለታል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1559.- ሌሎች መዝገቦች.

የግብርና ዲፓርትመንት ተጨማሪ መዝገቦች በአጠቃላይ መመሪያ ወይም በተለይ ለአንድ ወይም ከዚያ በላይ በሆኑ የጥበቃ ቦታዎች ላይ በሚተገበር መመሪያ መያዙን ሊወስን ይችላል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1560.- መዝገቦች ሊሰረዙ አይችሉም.

የሪል እስቴት መዝገብ በማንኛውም ሁኔታ ከተያያዘበት ቦታ ሊወገድ አይችልም.

ስነ ጥበብ. 1561.- የመመዝገቢያ ማስታወቂያ. -1 መመሪያዎች.

የሪል እስቴት ምዝገባ ለሕዝብ ይገኛል።

ስነ ጥበብ. 1562.- 2. የሪል እስቴት እና የባለቤቶች ምዝገባ.

(፩) የመዝገብ ጠባቂዎቹ በጠየቁት ጊዜ በሪል እስቴት መዛግብት ውስጥ የተካተቱትን ቅጠሎች የተመሰከረ እውነተኛ ቅጂዎችን ስለ ንብረቱ ጉዳይ ማቅረብ አለባቸው።
(፪) በባለቤቶች መዝገብ ውስጥ የሚገኙትን የአንድን ባለሀብት ቅጠሉ ወይም ቅጠሉ የተረጋገጠ እውነተኛ ቅጂ ሲጠየቅ አቅርቧል።
(፫) አስፈላጊ ሆኖ ሲገኝ የማይንቀሳቀሰው ንብረት ቅጠል ምንም ዓይነት ምዝገባ የሌለበት መሆኑን ወይም ስለ አንድ ባለንብረት 1 ምዝገባ የሚመለከት ቅጠል እንደሌለ የሚያሳይ ማስረጃ ማቅረብ አለባቸው።</item>
        <item>አስተዳደራዊ ኮንትራቶች
ምዕራፍ 1. አጠቃላይ ድንጋጌዎች
ስነ ጥበብ. 3131 - ለአስተዳደር አካላት ኮንትራቶች ተፈፃሚነት ያላቸው ደንቦች.
(፩) በመንግሥት ወይም በሌሎች የአስተዳደር ባለ ሥልጣናት የሚዋዋሉት ውሎች የሚተዳደሩት በዚህ ሕግ ስለ አጠቃላይ ውሎች ወይም ልዩ ውሎች በተመለከቱት ድንጋጌዎች ነው።
(፪) ስምምነቱ የአስተዳደር ስምምነት የሆነ እንደ ሆነ የዚህ የባለቤትነት መብት ድንጋጌዎች ከዚህ ድንጋጌዎች በተጨማሪ ወይም ይተካሉ።
ስነ ጥበብ. 3132 - የአስተዳደር ስምምነቶች.
ስምምነቱ እንደ አስተዳደራዊ ስምምነት ይቆጠራል፡-
(ሀ) በሕግ ወይም በተዋዋይ ወገኖች እንደዚሁ በግልጽ ብቁ ነው; ወይ
(ለ) ከአስተዳደር አካላት ጋር የሚዋዋለው አካል በዚህ አገልግሎት አፈጻጸም ውስጥ ቋሚ ተሳትፎን የሚያመለክት ከሆነ ከሕዝብ አገልግሎት እንቅስቃሴ ጋር የተያያዘ; ወይ
(ሐ) በግለሰቦች መካከል ካለው ግንኙነት ውጭ የጋራ ጥቅምን ወዲያውኑ በማጤን ብቻ ሊነሳሳ የሚችል አንድ ወይም ብዙ ድንጋጌዎች ይዟል.
ስነ ጥበብ. 3133 - ለተወሰኑ ንግዶች ማመልከቻ.
ለመንግስት ቁጠባ የሚያመለክቱ ወይም አክሲዮኖቻቸውን ለህዝብ የሚያቀርቡ የንግድ ድርጅቶች ውላቸውን በማጠናቀቅ ተቆጣጣሪ አካላት በህግ የተደነገጉትን ሂደቶች እና ስርዓቶች እንዲያከብሩ ስልጣን ያላቸው ባለስልጣናት ሊጠየቁ ይችላሉ.
ክፍል 1. ኮንትራት
አንቀጽ 1. ፍቃድ
ስነ ጥበብ. 3134 - ተቀባይነት ያለው ቅርጸት.
(፩) በአስተዳደር ሕጎች ወይም ደንቦች ተቃራኒ ድንጋጌ ከሌለ በቀር የአስተዳደር ባለሥልጣኖች የውል ማጠቃለያ በእነርሱ በኩል ግልጽ የሆነ የፍላጎት መግለጫን ያሳያል።
(፪) ውልን ለማጽደቅ ሥልጣን ያለው ባለሥልጣን ዝም ባለ ጊዜ መደበኛ ድንጋጌ ከሌለ ዝምታ እንደ ማረጋገጫ አይቆጠርም።
(፫) የንኡስ ቁጥር ድንጋጌዎች። (፩) እና (፪) ውሉን ለማራዘም ወይም ለማሻሻል ተፈጻሚ ይሆናሉ።
ስነ ጥበብ. 3135 - ለአስተዳደር ኮንትራቶች ተፈፃሚነት ያላቸው አጠቃላይ ሁኔታዎች. - 1. ስዕል መሳል.
የሞዴል ዝርዝር መግለጫዎች, አጠቃላይ አንቀጾች እና አጠቃላይ ውሎች እና ሁኔታዎች እና መመሪያዎች በእያንዳንዱ ፍላጎት አስተዳዳሪዎች ሊዘጋጁ ይችላሉ</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="c2">
        <item>ምዕራፍ 1 under list 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 3</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="detailsc2">
        <item>list second android </item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter  gsyfgthyri hygfuiyhi8u yguity</item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="c3">
        <item>ምዕራፍ 1</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 3</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 4</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="detailsc3">
        <item>chapter1 details lis 3</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="c4">
        <item>ምዕራፍ 1 </item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 3</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 4</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="detailsc4">
        <item>chapter1 details list 4 </item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="c5">
        <item>ምዕራፍ 1</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 3</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 4</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="detailsc5">
        <item>chapter1 details under [odstiuon 5</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="c6">
        <item>ምዕራፍ 1</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 3</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 4</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="detailsc6">
        <item>chapter1 details</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="c7">
        <item>ምዕራፍ 1</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 3</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 4</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="detailsc7">
        <item>ምዕራፍ details</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="c8">
        <item>ምዕራፍ 1</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 3</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 4</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="detailsc8">
        <item>chapter1 details under the last one admistration</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="kode1">
        <item>Mat-Dure I Seera Nama Dhunfaa  </item>
        <item>Mat-Dure II DANDEETTII NAMOOTA</item>
        <item>Mat-Dure III QAAMOOTA DHAABBATA FI QABEENYA BAKKA ADDA ADDAA QABAN </item>
        <item>Mat-Dure IV MAATII FI DHUKKUBA DHAABBATA</item>
        <item>Mat-Dure V ITTI FUFIINSA(MILKAHINAA)</item>
        <item>Mat-Dure VI Seera Nama Dhunfaa  </item>
        <item>Mat-Dure VII MEESHALEE WALIIGALAA FI QABANNI </item>
        <item>Mat-Dure VIII ABBUMMAA DHUUNFAA</item>
        <item>Mat-Dure IX ABBUMMAA WALDAA, USUFRUCT FI MIRGOOTA BIRAA RAM KEESSATTI</item>
        <item>Mat-Dure X GALMEESSOOTA QABEENYA HIN SOCHA’E </item>
        <item>Mat-Dure XI KONTIRAATA BULCHIINSAA</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="dubbisa1">
        <item>
Sirni seeraa Impaayera Keenya sirnaan akka guddatu seera siviilii koodii ta’e tumamuun barbaachisaa waan ta’eef; fi
Seerri Siivilii to’annoo Keenya jalatti qophaa’ee hayyama Seenetii fi Mana Maree Itti Aanaa Keenyaa waan argateef;
AMMA KANAAF, akkaataa Heera Mootummaa Keenya Fooyya’ee Keewwata 34 fi 88 tiin Murtii Seenetii fi Mana Maree Itti Aanaa Keenya ni raggaasifna, murteewwan Seenetii fi Mana Maree Itti aanaa Keenya ni raggaasifnee akka armaan gadiitti labsina:
1. Labsiin kun “Labsii Seera Siivilii, 1960” jedhamee waamamuu ni danda’a.
2. Seerri Siivilii bara 1960, jildii addaatiin maxxanfamee akka Dhimma Addaa Lakk.2 bara 1960. Akka Dhimma Addaa Lakk.
Caamsaa 5ffaa bara 1960 kana Addis Ababaatti raawwatame
TSAHAFE TAEZAZ AKLILU HABTE WOLD
Itti aanaa muummicha ministeeraa fi Ministira Pen </item>
        <item>MATA DUREE II DANDEETTII NAMOOTA
Boqonnaa 1. Dudhaalee Waliigalaa
Aartii. 192.- Seera dandeettii.

Namni qaamaa kamiyyuu seeraan dandeettii akka hin qabne yoo labsame malee gochoota jireenya siiviilii hunda raawwachuuf dandeettii qaba.

Aartii. 193.- Qaama miidhamummaa waliigalaa.

Hir’inni qaamaa waliigalaa umurii ykn haala sammuu namootaa irratti ykn murtii isaan irratti darbe irratti hundaa’a.

Aartii. 194.- Qaama miidhamtoota addaa.

(1) Qaama miidhamummaan addaa sababa lammummaa namootaatiin yookiin hojii isaan hojjetaniin tumamuu ni danda’a.
(2) Akkaataa Mata Duree kana Boqonnaa 5 (Keewwata 389-393) fi seerota addaatiin kan tumame ta’u.

Aartii. 195.- Daangaa fedhii ofiitiin.

(1) Namni kamiyyuu gartokkoon illee mirga lammiilee fayyadamuu yookiin itti fayyadamuu dhiisuu hin danda’u.
(2) Mirgoota akkasii fayyadamuu yookiin itti fayyadamuu irratti daangeffamni fedhiidhaan kaa’ame kamiyyuu dantaa seera qabeessa ta’een yoo mirkanaa’e malee bu’aa hin qabu.

Aartii. 196.- Ragaa qaama miidhamummaa.

(1) Dandeettiin ni tilmaama.
(2) Namni kamiyyuu qaama miidhamummaa nama qaamaa himate namni sun qaama miidhamummaa jala ta’uu isaa mirkaneessuu qaba.

Aartii. 197.- Qaamolee dhaabbilee fi qabeenya bakka murtaa’e qaban.

Dandeettiin qaamolee dhaabbilee fi qabeenya bakka adda ta’e qaban, akkaataa uumama isaaniitiin, tumaalee isaan ilaallatan, .</item>
        <item>MATA DUREE III. QAAMOOTA DHAABBATA FI QABEENYA BAKKA ADDA ADDAA QABAN
Boqonnaa 1. Qaamolee bulchiinsaa fi Mana Kiristaanaa
Aartii. 394.- Mootummaan.

(1) Mootummaan seeraan akka nama tokkootti ilaalama.
(2) Akka kanaan karaa qaamolee isaatiin mirga uumama isaa wajjin walsimu hunda qabaachuu fi itti fayyadamuu ni danda’a.

Aartii. 395.- Qoodinsa xiqqaa naannoo Mootummaa.

(1) Teklay Guezats, Awradja Guezatas, Woreda fi Mektl-Woreda Guezats fi komunoonni magaalaa fi baadiyyaas mirga mirga ni qabaatu.
(2) Akka kanaan karaa qaamolee isaaniitiin mirga seera bulchiinsaatiin isaaniif kenname hunda qabaachuu fi itti fayyadamuu ni danda’u.
            Aartii. 396.- Ministeerota.

(1) Ministeerotni Mootummaa Impaayera Itophiyaa mirga mirgaa kan qabanidha.
(2) Akka kanaan karaa qaamolee isaaniitiin mirga seera bulchiinsaatiin isaaniif kenname hunda qabaachuu fi itti fayyadamuu ni danda’u.

Aartii. 397.- Abbootii taayitaa bulchiinsa mootummaa fi dhaabbilee.

Abbootiin taayitaa bulchiinsa mootummaa, waajjirri ykn dhaabbileen seera bulchiinsaatiin namummaan ifatti kennameef hundi akkuma ogummaan bitamtoota mirgaati.

Aartii. 398.- Mana Kiristaanaa Ortodoksii Itoophiyaa.

(1) Manni Kiristaanaa Ortodoksii Itoophiyaa seeraan akka nama tokkootti ilaalama.
(2) Akka kanaan karaa qaamolee isaatiin mirga seerota bulchiinsaatiin kenname hunda qabaachuu fi itti fayyadamuu ni danda’a.

Aartii. 399.- Mana amantaa, waldaa amantootaa fi mana amantii.

Manneen amantaa, waldoota amantootaa fi manneen amantii qaama Mana Kiristaanaa Ortodoksii Itoophiyaa ta’an akkuma ogummaatti haal-duree fi daangaa seera bulchiinsaatiin murtaa’een mirga kan qabanidha.
        Aartii. 400.- Aangoo fi qaamolee.

(1) Aangoon qaamolee keewwata armaan olitti ibsaman akkasumas qaamolee qaamolee akkasii bakka bu’uuf hayyamaman seera bulchiinsaatiin ni tumama.
(2) Mirgoota murtaa’an hojiirra oolchuuf haal-duree yookiin sirna murtaa’e akka kabajamu qaamolee akkasii irratti fe’uu ni danda’u.

Aartii. 401.- Ulaagaalee seeraa guutuu dhabuu.

(1) Gochoonni qaamolee Boqonnaa kana keessatti ibsaman haal-duree sirnaa seeraan barbaadamu osoo hin eegin aangoo seeraan isaaniif kenname caalaa raawwatan bu’aa tokkollee hin qabaatan.
(2) Tumaalee keewwata xiqqaa. (1) haala akkasii keessatti seeraan ifatti kan hin tumamne ta’us raawwatiinsa ni qabaata.

Aartii. 402.- Nuulii ta’uu.

(1) Kwt. 401 qaama fedhii qabu kamiinuu waamamuu ni danda’a.
(2) Guyyaa gochi sun raawwatame irraa eegalee waggaa kudhan erga darbee booda kana booda waamamuu hin danda’u.

Aartii. 403.- Itti gaafatamummaa waliigaltee ala.

(1) Qaamoleen Boqonnaa kana keessatti ibsaman akkaataa tumaalee Mata Duree Seera kanaa “Itti Gaafatamummaa Waliigaltee Alaa fi Badhaadhina Seeraan Alaa” ( Keewwata.2027-2161).
(2) Akkaataa tumaalee Mata duree walfakkaataatiin badhaadhina seeraan alaa argatan kamiyyuu ni kaffalu (Keewwata, 2162-2178).</item>
        <item>KITAABA II. MAATII FI DHUKKUBA DHAABBATA
MATA DUREE IV. HIDHAA HARIIROO HIDHAA FI FIROONNI
Boqonnaa 1. Hariiroo firoomaatiin fi walumaa galatti walitti dhufeenyaan
Aartii. 550.- Hariiroo uumamaa.

(1) Hidhoonni hariiroo uumamaa hawaasa dhiigaa irraa madda.
(2) Hidhamiinsi hariiroo sanyiitiin jira, sarara kallatti olka’aa fi sanyii gidduu jiru keessatti.
(3) Sarara wabii keessatti namoota olka’aa waliigalaa tokkoo fi isaa ol irraa bu’an gidduutti argama.

Aartii. 551.- Sadarkaa hariiroo firummaatiin.

(1) Sadarkaan walitti dhufeenya sanyiitiin sarara wabii keessatti argamu sarara tokkoon tokkoon isaanii keessatti dhaloota torba akaakayyuu waliinii irraa lakkaa’uudhaan shallagama.
(2) Hariiroon firummaa dhaloota torbaffaa booda bu’aa tokkollee hin qabaatu.
        Aartii. 552.- Walitti dhufeenya.

(1) Hidhamiinsi walitti dhufeenyaa gaa’ela irraa madda.
(2) Hidhamiinsi walitti dhufeenyaa, sarara kallattiin, nama tokkoo fi olka’oota ykn sanyii haadha warraa gidduutti ni jira.
(3) Sarara wabii keessatti nama tokkoo fi wabii haadha warraa isaa gidduutti argama.

Aartii. 553.- Daangaa hanga sadarkaa sadaffaatti.

Firoomni sarara wabii sadarkaa sadaffaa irra darbee bu’aa tokkollee hin qabu.

Aartii. 554.- Firooma dachaa.

(1) Hidhamni firooma dachaa nama tokkoo fi haadha warraa namoota inni walitti dhufeenyaan walitti dhufeenya qabu gidduutti ni jira.
(2) Hidhamni firooma dachaa akkasii bu’aa a fi firooma salphaa wajjin walfakkaatu ni fida.
Aartii. 555.- Firooma dhaabuu.
Gaa’elli ittiin uumame diigamus hidhni walitti dhufeenyaa sarara kallattiifi wabii keessatti ni jiraata.</item>
        <item>MATA DUREE V. ITTI FUFIINSA
Boqonnaa. 1. Jijjiirama Walduraa duubaa
Keewwata 1. Tumaalee Waliigalaa
Keewwata 1.- Baniinsa walduraa duubaa fi wantoota walduraa duubaan uumuu

Aartii. 826.- Baniinsa walduraa duubaa.
(1) Namni tokko bakka du’etti, walduraa duubaan nama akkasii, kan du’e jedhamee waamamu, yeroo du’a isaa bakka jireenya isaa isa guddaa tureetti ni banama.
.

Aartii. 827.- Wantoota dhaala uumuu.-1. Inshuraansii jireenyaa.

(1) Maallaqni waliigaltee inshuraansii jireenyaa namni du’e qaama itti hirmaate raawwachuudhaan kaffalamuu qabu, namni du’e fayyadamaa murteessuu kan hin dandeenye yoo ta’e yookiin inshuraansii dhaaltota nama du’ee osoo hin taane fayyadamoo kan ta’e yoo ta’e qaama dhaala ta’a agarsiiftuu biraa kamiyyuu.
(2) Haala birootiin qaama dhaala sanaa hin ta’an.
        Aartii. 829.- Walduraa duubaan gosa adda addaa.

(1) Walduraa duubaan nama du’ee dhaala yookiin dhaala ta’uu danda’a.
(2) Gara tokkoon dhaala kan hin qabne, gartokkoon immoo dhaala kan hin qabne ta’uu danda’a.
(3) Qabeenyi namni du’e fedhiidhaan hin fudhanne dhaaltota seeraa isaaf ni kennama.

Keewwata2. Dandeettii Milkaa’uu
Aartii. 830.- Haal-duree milkaa’uuf barbaachisan.

Namni tokko nama du’e sana yoo lubbuun hafee fi bakka bu’uuf kan hin malle ta’e malee bakka bu’uu dhiisuu danda’a.

Aartii. 831.- Jireenya dhaaltuu nama du’ee.

(1) Namni tokko guyyaa du’a nama du’etti jiraachuu isaa ragaan akkaataa tumaalee Mata Duree Seera kanaa “Namoota Qaama” (Keewwata 47-153) ilaallataniin ta’a.
(2) Bu’aa dhabamuu ilaalchisee tumaaleen Mata Duree walfakkaataa raawwatiinsa ni qabaatu (Keewwata 154-173).
(3) Keewwata kana keessatti wanti tumaalee bakka bu’ummaa walduraa duubaan ilaallatan irratti dhiibbaa hin geessisu.

Aartii. 832.- Namoota yeroo tokkotti du’an.

Namoonni lamaa fi isaa ol du’anii fi namoota akkasii keessaa kamtu isa kaan irraa hafe mirkaneessuun kan hin danda’amne yoo ta’e, walduraa duubaan namoota akkasii tokkoon tokkoon isaanii isa kaan irraa akka hafe mirkaneessuun kan hin danda’amne yoo ta’e, walduraa duubaan namoota akkasii tokkoon tokkoon isaanii akka waan tureetti ni qajeelfama kan dhumaa lubbuun hafe with out, garuu, walduraa duubaan namoota biroo irraa waan tokkollee argachuu.</item>

        <item>
        MATA DUREE VI MEESHALEE WALIIGALAA FI QABANNI
Boqonnaa 1. Meeshaalee akka waliigalaatti
Keewwata .1126. Meeshaalee gosa adda addaa.
Meeshaaleen hundi kan socho’an ykn kan hin sochoone dha.

Aartii. 1127.- Qabeenya qaamaa.- 1. Prinsippii.

Qabeenyi qaamaa wantoota jiraachuu qaamaa qabaniifi amala dhuunfaa isaanii osoo hin dhabin of sochoosuu ykn namaan sochoosuu danda’aniidha.

Keewwata .1128.- 2. Sekuritiiwwan gara baattuutti.

Seeraan haala biraatiin yoo tumame malee, himannaan fi mirgoonni qaama hin qabne biroo sekuritiiwwan keessatti hammataman to bearer akka qabeenya qaamaatti ni fudhatamu.

Aartii. 1129. 3. Humnoota uumamaa.

Seeraan haala biraatiin yoo tumame malee humnoonni uumamaa gatii dinagdee qaban kan akka humna ibsaa bakka namni itti qabamee itti fayyadama isaaf oolcheetti akka meeshaalee qaamaa ta’anii fudhatamu.

Aartii. 1130.- Wantoota hin sochoone.

Lafti fi gamoo akka hin sochooneetti ni fudhatama.

Aartii. 1131.- Qaamolee keessaa meeshaalee. 1. Qajeelfama.

Haala biraatiin yoo tumame malee, mirgoonni meeshaalee irratti, yookiin walitti dhufeenyi meeshaalee waliin walqabatan qaamolee keessaa hunda irratti raawwatiinsa ni qabaatu.

Aartii. 1132.- 2. Hiika.

(1) Wanti aadaatiin qaama waan tokkoo akka ta’etti ilaalamu kamiyyuu qaama keessaa ta’ee fudhatama.
(2) Wanti qaamaan waan tokko waliin walitti makamee fi waan akkasii osoo hin balleessin yookiin osoo hin miidhin achirraa adda baafamuu kan hin dandeenye kamiyyuu qaama keessaa isa keessaa ta’ee fudhatama.

Aartii. 1133.- 3. Mukaa fi korporeeshinii.

(1) Mukkeen fi korporeeshiniin hanga lafa irraa adda ba’anitti qaama keessaa ta’uu qabu.
(2) Lafa irraa adda ba’uu isaaniif waliigalteewwan godhaman yookiin addaan ba’uu akkasii kan agarsiisu yoo ta’e, meeshaalee qaamaa adda ta’anitti ni ilaalamu.

Aartii. 1134.- 4. Mirga qaama sadaffaa.

(1) Wanti qaama keessaa socho’aa yookiin hin sochoone ta’e wanta adda ta’e uumuu ni dhiisa.
(2) Mirgi qaamni sadaffaan kanaan dura waan akkasii irratti qaban hundi ni dhaama.
(3) Mirga qaamni sadaffaan akkasii itti gaafatamummaa miidhaa ykn badhaadhina seeraan alaa irratti hundaa’uun himannaa dhiyeessu irratti dhiibbaa kan geessisu hin jiru.
    </item>

        <item>
            MATA DUREE VII. ABBUMMAA DHUUNFAA
BOQONNAA 1. Argachuu, dabarsuu, dhabamsiisuu fi ragaa abbummaa
Kutaa 1. Abbummaa argachuu
Keewwata 1. Hojii
Aartii. 1151.- Qajeelfama.

Namni qabeenya qaamaa abbaa qabeenyaa ta’uuf yaadamee gooftaa hin qabne qabate abbummaa qabeenya akkasii ni argata.

Aartii. 1152.- Bineensota.

(1) Bineensonni leenjifaman yookiin booji’aman to’annoo abbaa qabeenyaa isaanii jalaa miliqanii fi ji’a itti aanu keessatti deebisee qabachuuf hin yaalne yookiin deebi’ee qabachuuf yaaluun ji’a tokkoof kan dhaabe waan gooftaa hin qabne ta’a.
(2) Tumaaleen keewwata xiqqaa (1) bineensota gosa fardaa yookiin asinine yookiin walhormaata isaanii yookiin gaalaafi bineensota gosa loonii irratti raawwatiinsa hin qabaatan.

Aartii. 1153.- Beeylada.

(1) Tuutni beeyladaa qamadii isaanii keessaa ba’e akka waan gooftaa hin qabneetti ilaalamu.
(2) Namni isaan qamadii isaa keessa qubatan sababa qabachuu isaatiin abbaa tuuta akkasii ta’a.
(3) Abbaan qabeenyaa duraanii bakka isaan ari’etti deebisee fudhatee battaluma sanatti bakka qubatan ga’uu ni danda’a.

Aartii. 1154.- Wanti argame.- 1. Dirqama barbaadaa.

(1) Namni meeshaa qaamaa argate fi qabate dambiiwwan bulchiinsaa argannoo isaa akka gabaasu gaafatu ni eega.
(2) Dambiiwwan akkanaa yoo hin baane, argannoo isaa beeksisuuf tarkaanfii barbaachisaa ta’e hunda fudhachuu fi qorannoo haalawwan keessatti barbaachisu ni taasisa, abbaa argannoo isaa beeksisuuf yaada.

Aartii. 1155.- 2. Meeshaa qabachuu.

(1) Barbaattuun dirqama keewwata 10 jalatti tumame raawwate. 1154 wanta argame harka isaa keessa ni qabata.
(2) Haala akkanaa keessatti kunuunsuuf tarkaanfiiwwan madaalawaa ta’an hunda ni fudhata.
        </item>

        <item>
            MATA DUREE VIII ABBUMMAA WALDAA, USUFRUCT FI MIRGOOTA BIRAA RAM KEESSATTI

Boqonnaa 1. Abbummaa waliinii
Keewwata 1. Tumaalee waliigalaa
Aartii. 1257.- Qajeelfama.

(1) Wanti tokko akka abbootii qabeenyaa waliinii namoota hedduudhaan qabaachuu ni danda’a.
(2) Dambiiwwan hawaasa qonnaa fi waldaalee ofiisaa abbootii qabeenyaa ilaallatan kan seera kana Mata duree IX keessatti tumaman irratti wanti tokkollee dhiibbaa hin geessisu. (Keewwata 1489-1534).

Aartii. 1258.- Abbummaa waliinii akkamitti qajeelfama.

(1) Tumaalee dirqamaa labsichaa osoo hin tuqin mirgi fi dirqamni abbootii qabeenyaa waliinii meeshaa abbummaan waliinii irraa maddu fi waliigalteewwan abbootiin qabeenyaa waliinii raawwatan jalatti kan bitamu ta’a.
(2) Tumaaleen akkanaa meeshaan yookiin waliigalteewwan keewwata xiqqaa jalatti ibsaman kan hin jirre yoo ta’e raawwatiinsa ni qabaatu. (1) kan hojjetaman yookiin meeshaan yookiin waliigalteewwan akkasii mudaa kan qaban yookiin seeraan kan faallessu yoo ta’e.

Aartii. 1259.- Tilmaama walqixxummaa.

Aksiyooniin tokkoon tokkoon abbaa qabeenyaa waliinii qaban walqixa akka ta’etti fudhatama.

Aartii. 1260.- Mirga aksiyoonaa irratti.

(1) Tokkoon tokkoon abbaa qabeenyaa waliinii qooda isaa gatuu ykn wabii kennuu ni danda’a.
(2) Liqeessitoonni abbaa qabeenyaa waliinii tokkoon tokkoon isaanii aksiyoona isaa walitti qabsiisuu ni danda’u.
Aartii. 1261.- Mirga seeraa dursee bitachuu.
(1) Abbootiin qabeenyaa waliinii qaamni sadaffaan wanta waliin qaban sana keessaa qooda argate kamiyyuu akka isaanitti gurguruuf dirqisiisuuf mirga seeraan ni qabaatu.
(2) Mirgi keewwata xiqqaa, (1) jalatti ibsame haala Mata Duree kana Boqonnaa 4 (Keewwata 1386-1409) jalatti tumameen ni raawwatama.

Aartii. 1262.- Aksiyoona harka kennachuu.

(1) Abbaan qabeenyaa waliinii tokko wanta waliin qabame keessatti qooda isaa kan kenne yoo ta’e, qoodni sun abbootii qabeenyaa waliinii biroof ni kuufama.
(2) Abbaan qabeenyaa waliinii qooda isaa dabarsee kenne liqaa dabarsee kennuu isaa dura itti gaafatamummaa qabuuf itti gaafatamummaa ni qabaata.

Aartii. 1263. Fayyadama waan tokkoo.

Tokkoon tokkoon abbaa qabeenyaa waliinii meeshaa waliin qabame akkaataa kaayyoo itti argamee fi mirga abbootii qabeenyaa waliinii biroo ilaalcha sirrii ta’een itti fayyadamuu ni danda’a.

Aartii. 1664.- Dabala.

(1) Firiin wanta waliin qabame tokkoo waliin ta’a.
(2) Tokkoon tokkoon abbaa qabeenyaa waliinii yeroo barbaadetti firiiwwan akkasii akka qoodaman iyyachuu ni danda’a.

Aartii. 1265.- Bulchiinsa waan waliin qabame.-1. Bulchiinsa harka caalu.
        </item>

        <item>
            MATA DUREE X. GALMEESSOOTA QABEENYA HIN SOCHA’E
Boqonnaa 1. Galmee fi beeksisa qabachuu
Aartii. 1553.- Qajeelfama.

Galmeen qabeenya hin sochoone, tokkoon tokkoon Awradja Guezat Impaayera Itoophiyaa keessatti, eegdota galmee qabeenya hin sochooneen ni qabama.

Aartii. 1554.- Gurmaa’ina iddoowwan kunuunsa galmeewwanii.

(1) Muudamni fi sadarkaan eegdota galmee qabeenya hin sochoonee fi gargaartota isaanii akkaataa Ministeera Qonnaatiin tumame ta’a.
(2) Ministeerichi gurmaa’ina meeshaa iddoowwan kunuunsa galmeewwan qabeenya hin sochoone ni murteessa, hojiin isaaniis sirnaan akka raawwatamu ni taasisa.
(3) Galmee qabeenya hin sochoone eeguu fi kunuunsuuf tarkaanfiiwwan barbaachisoo ta’an ni fudhata.

Aartii. 1555.- Aanaalee lafti itti qoodamu.

(1) Galmeen qabeenya hin sochoone, bakka kunuunsaa tokkoon tokkoon isaatti, akkaataa aanaalee lafti itti qoodameetti ni qabama.
(2) Ministeerri Qonnaa daangaa aanaalee lafti itti qoodame ni murteessa.

Aartii. 1556.- Galmee ijoo.

Tokkoon tokkoon iddoo kunuunsaa fi tokkoon tokkoon aanaatiif galmeen qabeenyaa fi galmeen liqii manaa ni qabama.

Aartii. 1557.- Galmee meeshaalee hin sochoone.

Haalli kaadaastirichaa sirna akkanaa akka fudhatamu kan hayyamu yoo ta’e, tokkoon tokkoon aanaa keessatti galmeen meeshaalee hin sochoone ni qabama.

Aartii. 1558.- Galmee abbootii qabeenyaa.

Naannoon kaadaastirichaa galmee meeshaalee hin sochoone akka qophaa’u kan hin hayyamne yoo ta’e, galmee akkasii dhiisanii aanaa tokkoon tokkoon isaanii keessatti galmeen abbootii qabeenyaa ni qabama.

Aartii. 1559.- Galmeewwan biroo.

Ministeerri Qonnaa qajeelfama waliigalaatiin, yookiin qajeelfama addatti bakka kunuunsa tokkoo fi isaa ol irratti raawwatiinsa qabuun galmeewwan dabalataa akka qabaman murteessuu ni danda’a.

Aartii. 1560.- Galmeewwan haqamuu hin danda’an.

Galmeen qabeenya hin sochoone haala kamiinuu bakka itti qabame irraa kaafamuu hin danda’u.

Aartii. 1561.- Galmeewwan beeksisuu. -1. Qajeelfama.

Galmeen qabeenya hin sochoone ummataaf kan dhiyaatudha.

Aartii. 1562.- 2. Galmee meeshaalee hin sochoone fi kan abbootii qabeenyaa.

(1) Eegdonni galmee, gaaffii yoo dhiyeessan, waraabbii dhugaa mirkanaa’e baala kan hin sochoone addaa ilaalchisee galmeewwan hin sochoone keessatti argamu ni dhiyeessu.
(2) Gaaffii yoo dhiyeessan kooppii dhugaa mirkanaa’e baala yookiin baala abbaa qabeenyaa murtaa’e ilaallatu galmee abbootii qabeenyaa keessatti argamuu qabu ni dhiyeessu.
(3) Bakka barbaachisaa ta’etti baalli meeshaa hin sochoone galmee tokkollee akka hin qabne yookiin baalli abbaa qabeenyaa murtaa’e ilaallatu akka hin jirre agarsiisu ragaa ni dhiyeessu I galmee.
        </item>


        <item>MATA DUREE X. GALMEESSOOTA QABEENYA HIN SOCHA’E
Boqonnaa 1. Galmee fi beeksisa qabachuu
Aartii. 1553.- Qajeelfama.

Galmeen qabeenya hin sochoone, tokkoon tokkoon Awradja Guezat Impaayera Itoophiyaa keessatti, eegdota galmee qabeenya hin sochooneen ni qabama.

Aartii. 1554.- Gurmaa’ina iddoowwan kunuunsa galmeewwanii.

(1) Muudamni fi sadarkaan eegdota galmee qabeenya hin sochoonee fi gargaartota isaanii akkaataa Ministeera Qonnaatiin tumame ta’a.
(2) Ministeerichi gurmaa’ina meeshaa iddoowwan kunuunsa galmeewwan qabeenya hin sochoone ni murteessa, hojiin isaaniis sirnaan akka raawwatamu ni taasisa.
(3) Galmee qabeenya hin sochoone eeguu fi kunuunsuuf tarkaanfiiwwan barbaachisoo ta’an ni fudhata.

Aartii. 1555.- Aanaalee lafti itti qoodamu.

(1) Galmeen qabeenya hin sochoone, bakka kunuunsaa tokkoon tokkoon isaatti, akkaataa aanaalee lafti itti qoodameetti ni qabama.
(2) Ministeerri Qonnaa daangaa aanaalee lafti itti qoodame ni murteessa.

Aartii. 1556.- Galmee ijoo.

Tokkoon tokkoon iddoo kunuunsaa fi tokkoon tokkoon aanaatiif galmeen qabeenyaa fi galmeen liqii manaa ni qabama.

Aartii. 1557.- Galmee meeshaalee hin sochoone.

Haalli kaadaastirichaa sirna akkanaa akka fudhatamu kan hayyamu yoo ta’e, tokkoon tokkoon aanaa keessatti galmeen meeshaalee hin sochoone ni qabama.

Aartii. 1558.- Galmee abbootii qabeenyaa.

Naannoon kaadaastirichaa galmee meeshaalee hin sochoone akka qophaa’u kan hin hayyamne yoo ta’e, galmee akkasii dhiisanii aanaa tokkoon tokkoon isaanii keessatti galmeen abbootii qabeenyaa ni qabama.

Aartii. 1559.- Galmeewwan biroo.

Ministeerri Qonnaa qajeelfama waliigalaatiin, yookiin qajeelfama addatti bakka kunuunsa tokkoo fi isaa ol irratti raawwatiinsa qabuun galmeewwan dabalataa akka qabaman murteessuu ni danda’a.

Aartii. 1560.- Galmeewwan haqamuu hin danda’an.

Galmeen qabeenya hin sochoone haala kamiinuu bakka itti qabame irraa kaafamuu hin danda’u.

Aartii. 1561.- Galmeewwan beeksisuu. -1. Qajeelfama.

Galmeen qabeenya hin sochoone ummataaf kan dhiyaatudha.

Aartii. 1562.- 2. Galmee meeshaalee hin sochoone fi kan abbootii qabeenyaa.

(1) Eegdonni galmee, gaaffii yoo dhiyeessan, waraabbii dhugaa mirkanaa’e baala kan hin sochoone addaa ilaalchisee galmeewwan hin sochoone keessatti argamu ni dhiyeessu.
(2) Gaaffii yoo dhiyeessan kooppii dhugaa mirkanaa’e baala yookiin baala abbaa qabeenyaa murtaa’e ilaallatu galmee abbootii qabeenyaa keessatti argamuu qabu ni dhiyeessu.
(3) Bakka barbaachisaa ta’etti baalli meeshaa hin sochoone galmee tokkollee akka hin qabne yookiin baalli abbaa qabeenyaa murtaa’e ilaallatu akka hin jirre agarsiisu ragaa ni dhiyeessu I galmee.</item>
        <item>
            KONTIRAATA BULCHIINSAA
Boqonnaa 1. Tumaalee waliigalaa
Aartii. 3131 – Dambiiwwan waliigaltee qaamolee bulchiinsaa irratti raawwatiinsa qaban.
(1) Waliigalteewwan Mootummaan yookiin qaamolee bulchiinsaa birootiin raawwataman tumaalee seera kanaa waliigalteewwan waliigalaa yookiin waliigaltee addaatiin walqabataniin kan bulfaman ta’a.
(2) Tumaaleen Mata Duree kanaa tumaalee akkasii kan dabalu yookiin bakka bu’u waliigaltichi maalummaa waliigaltee bulchiinsaa yoo ta’e.
Aartii. 3132 – Waliigalteewwan bulchiinsaa.
Waliigaltichi waliigaltee bulchiinsaa ta’ee kan ilaalamu yoo ta’u:
(a) seeraan yookiin gareewwan falmitootaan ifatti akkas ta’uuf ulaagaa kan guute yoo ta’e; yookaan
(b) sochii tajaajila mootummaa waliin kan walqabatu yoo ta’u, qaamni qaamolee bulchiinsaa waliin waliigaltee raawwate tajaajila akkasii raawwachuu keessatti hirmaannaa dhaabbataa kan agarsiisu yoo ta’e; yookaan
(c) tumaalee tokko yookiin isaa ol kan of keessaa qabu yoo ta’u, kunis ilaalcha hatattamaa faayidaa waliigalaa hariiroo namoota dhuunfaa gidduu jiruun ala ta’e qofaan kaka’uu danda’a.
Aartii. 3133 – Dhaabbilee daldalaa murtaa’aniif hojiirra oolmaa.
Dhaabbileen daldalaa qusannoo mootummaaf iyyata dhiyeessan yookiin aksiyoona isaanii ummata bira kaa’an, waliigaltee isaanii xumuruun, hojimaataa fi sirna seeraan qaamolee bulchiinsaatiif tumame akka eegan qaamolee aangoo qabuun dirqisiisuu ni danda’u.
Kutaa 1. Waliigaltee uumuu
Keewwata 1. Hayyama
Aartii. 3134 – Bifa fudhatama.
(1) Seerota yookiin dambiiwwan bulchiinsaatiin haala biraatiin yoo tumame malee, waliigaltee tokko qaamolee bulchiinsaatiin xumuruun fedhii gama isaaniitiin ifatti mul’isuu kan agarsiisudha.
(2) Abbaan taayitaa waliigaltee tokko raggaasisuuf aangoo qabu yoo callise, callisuun akkasii tumaan sirnaa yoo hin jiraanne akka raggaasifamuutti hin ilaalamu.
(3) Tumaalee keewwata xiqqaa. (1) fi (2) waliigaltee tokko dheeressuu, ykn fooyya’iinsa irratti raawwatiinsa ni qabaatu.
Aartii. 3135 – Haala waliigalaa waliigalteewwan bulchiinsaa irratti raawwatiinsa qaban. – 1. Fakkii kaasuu.
Ispeesifikeeshiniiwwan moodeela, keeyyata waliigalaa fi haal-duree fi qajeelfamni waliigalaa tokkoon tokkoon bulchitoota fedhii qabaniin qophaa’uu ni danda’u
        </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="kode2">
        <item> SIIVIILII</item>
        <item>Daangaa Hojiirra Oolmaa</item>
        <item> AANGOO MANA MURTII</item>
        <item>Daangaa hojiirra oolmaa</item>
        <item>HOJII ILAALCHA SADARKAA JALQABAA IRRATTI</item>
        <item> HOJAMAA ADDAA</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="dubbisa2">
         <item>Seensa


TSAHAFE TAEZAZ AKLILU HABTE WOLD
Ministirri Muummee fi Ministira Pen</item>
        <item>

Keewwata 4- Manneen murtii yoo dhorkame malee himata akka ilaalan
 </item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter  gsyfgthyri hygfuiyhi8u yguity</item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="kode3">
        <item>Boqonna 1</item>
        <item>Boqonna 2</item>
        <item>Boqonna 3</item>
        <item>Boqonna 4</item>
        <item>Boqonna 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="dubbisa3">
        <item>chapter1 details lis 3</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="kode4">
        <item>Boqonna 1 </item>
        <item>Boqonna 2</item>
        <item>Boqonna 3</item>
        <item>chapter 4</item>
        <item>chapter 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="dubbisa4">
        <item>chapter1 details list 4 </item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="kode5">
        <item>Boqonna 1</item>
        <item>Boqonna 2</item>
        <item>Boqonna 3</item>

    </string-array>
    <string-array name="dubbisa5">
        <item>chapter1 details under [odstiuon 5</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="kode6">
        <item>Boqonna 1</item>
        <item>Boqonna 2</item>
        <item>Boqonna 3</item>
        <item>Boqonna 4</item>
        <item>Boqonna 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="dubbisa6">
        <item>chapter1 details</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="kode7">
        <item>Boqonna 1</item>
        <item>Boqonna 2</item>
        <item>Boqonna 3</item>
        <item>Boqonna 4</item>
        <item>Boqonna 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="dubbisa7">
        <item>chapter1 details</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="kode8">
        <item>Boqonna 1</item>
        <item>Boqonna 2</item>
        <item>Boqonna 3</item>
        <item>Boqonna 4</item>
        <item>Boqonna 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="dubbisa8">
        <item>chapter1 details under the last one admistration</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>Boqonna 5 gadifagenyaa isaa </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="e1">
        <item>Title I: Physical Persons</item>
        <item>Title II: Capacity of People</item>
        <item> Title III: Entities Corporate and Property with a Specific Destination </item>
        <item>Title IV: Relationship and Friendship</item>
        <item>Title V: Achievements</item>
        <item>Title VI: Goods and Possessions in General</item>
        <item>Title VII: Individual Ownership</item>
        <item>Title VIII: Private Ownership</item>
        <item>Title IX Corporate Ownership, Use, and Other Rights in RAM</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="de1">
       <item>Civil Code:> PROCLAMATION No. 165 of 1960 THE CIVIL CODE PROCLAMATION OF 1980
CONQUERING LION OF THE TRIBE OF JUDAH
HAILE SELASSIE I
ELECT OF GOD, EMPEROR OF ETHIOPIA
WHEREAS it is essential to the orderly development of the legal system of Our Empire that a codified civil law be enacted; and
WHEREAS a Civil Code has been prepared under Our supervision and has received the approval of Our Senate and Chamber of Deputies;
NOW, THEREFORE, in accordance with Articles 34 and 88 Our Revised Constitution, We approve the resolution of Our Senate and Chamber of Deputies and We approve the resolutions of Our Senate and Chamber of Deputies and We hereby proclaim as follows:
1.    This proclamation may be cited as the “Civil Code Proclamation, 1960”
2.    The Civil Code of 1960, as published in a separate volume appearing as Extraordinary Issue No. 2 of 1960. As Extraordinary Issue No. 2 of 1960 of the Negarit Gazeta, shall come into force on the 11th day of September, 1960.
Done at Addis Ababa this 5th day of May, 1960 Section 1. Attribution of Personality
Art. 1.- Principle.
The human person is the subject of rights from its birth to its death.
Art.2.- Child merely conceived.
A child merely conceived shall be considered born whenever his interest so
demands, provided he is born alive and viable.
Art.3.- Date of conception.
(1)    A child shall be deemed to have been conceived on the three hundredth day which precedes his birth.
(2)    No proof shall be admitted against this presumption.
(3)    Nothing in this Article shall affect the provisions of this Code relating to the date of conception where it need be established who is  the father of the child.
Art 4.- Viable or not viable child.
(1)    A child shall be deemed to be viable where he lives for forty-eight hours after his birth, notwithstanding any proof to the contrary.
(2)    A child  shall be deemed to be not viable where he dies less than forty-eight hours after his birth.
(3)    The presumption laid down in sub-art. (2) may be rebutted by proving that the death of the child is due a cause other than a deficiency in his constitution.
Art.5- Proof of life or death of person. 1. Burden of proof.
(1)    Whosoever, for the purpose of exercising a right, alleges that a particular person is or was alive on a certain day, or is dead, shall prove the allegation.
(2)    The proof that a person is or was alive shall be made by producing the person himself or by the evidence of three witnesses or any other reliable evidence.
(3)    The proof of death shall be made in accordance with the provisions of Chapter 3 of this Title (art. 47).
Art. 6- 2. Persons dead simultaneously.
Where several persons are dead, and it is not possible to prove that one of such persons survived another, all these persons shall be deemed to have died at the same time.
Art.7- Proof of identity.
(1)    The identity of a person shall be proved by the documents issued to such person by the administrative authorities.
(2)    Failing such documents, it shall be proved by the production of two witnesses.
(3)    The witness shall be liable to third parties for the damage which may be caused through the inaccuracy of their declarations or evidence.
Section 2. Rights of Personality
Art. 8- Effect of personality.
(1)    Every physical person shall enjoy the rights of personality and the liberties guaranteed by the Ethiopian Constitution.
(2)    In this respect, no regard shall be had to the race, color, religion or sex of persons.
Art.9- Limitations to these effects.
(1)    The rights of personality and the liberties guaranteed by the Constitution are extra commercium.
(2)    Any voluntary limitation imposed on the exercise of such rights and liberties shall be of no effect unless it is justified by a legitimate interest.
Art. 10.- Cessation of unlawful molestations.
Any unlawful molestation to the personality shall give to the person who suffers it the right to demand that it be stopped, without prejudice to the liability of the author of such molestation.
Art.11.- Restriction on freedom and searches.
No person may have his freedom restricted, or be subjected to a search, except in the causes provided by law.
Art. 12.- Freedom of residence.
(1)    Every person is free to establish his residence wherever it is suitable for him and to  change the place of such residence.
(2)    The undertaking of a person to reside in a particular place shall be of no effect under civil law.
(3)    The undertaking of a person not to reside in or not to got to a particular place shall be of no effect unless it is justified by a legitimate interest.
Art.13- Inviolability of domicile.
(1)    The domicile of a physical person is inviolable
(2)    No one may enter the domicile of another against the will of such person, neither may a search be effected therein, except in the cases provided by law.
Art. 14.- Freedom of thought.
(1)    Every person is free to think and to express his ideas.
(2)    The only restrictions which this liberty admits of are those which are imposed by the respect for the rights of others, morality and the law.
Art. 15- Religion.
There shall be no interference with the exercise, in accordance with the law, of the rites of any religion or creed by residents of the Empire, provided that such rites be not utilized for political purposes or be not prejudicial to public order or morality.
Art.16.- Freedom of action.
(1)    Every  person is free to exercise any activity which he deems proper in that which concerns his calling and his leisure.
(2)    The only restrictions which such freedom admits of are those which are imposed by the respect for the rights of others, morality and the law.
(3)    The act by which a person binds himself to exercise a given activity or binds himself not exercise such activity shall be of no effect unless it is justified by a legitimate interest.
Art. 17.-  Marriage and divorce.
(1)    The undertaking of a person not to marry or not to remarry shall be of no effect under civil law.
(2)    This shall apply to the undertaking of a person to divorce or not to divorce.
Art. 18. Integrity of human body.
(1)    The act by which a person disposes of the whole or of a part of his body shall be of no effect under civil law where such act is to be carried out before the death of the person thus disposing, if such act has the effect of causing a serious injury to the integrity of the human body.
(2)    The provisions of sub-art. (1) shall not apply where the act is justified by the rules of medical practice.
Art. 19.- Revocability of acts relative thereto.
(1)    A person may at any time revoke the act by which he has disposed of the whole or a part of his body whether such act is to be carried out during the lifetime of the person by whom it was performed or after his death.
(2)    The person to whose advantage such act has been made has  the right to be indemnified for the expenses which he has incurred on the fait of such promise.
Art. 20- Medical examinations and treatment. -1. Principle.
(1)    A person may at any time refuse to submit himself to a medical or surgical examination or treatment.
(2)    Nothing in this Article shall  affect the provisions of laws or regulations providing for a physical examination of persons or their compulsory vaccination or other similar measures in the public interest,
(3)    Nothing in this Article shall affect the power of a guardian of a minor or interdicted person to submit the incapacitated person of whom he is in charge to an examination or treatment beneficial to that persons health.
Art.21.- 2. Restriction.
Where the examination or treatment to which a person is required to submit himself does not involve any abnormal risk, such person, in case of refusal, forfeits the rights to avail himself of the illness or infirmity which the treatment could have prevented, eliminated or lessened.
Art. 22. Medical examination
Where a person refuses to submit himself to a medical examination not involving any serious danger for the human body, the court may considers as established the facts which the examination had the object of ascertaining.
Art. 23.- Right to keep silent
Any  admission or manifestation of the will obtained by methods causing molestation to the personality shall be of no effect.
Art 24.- Professional secrecy:
(1)    A person may not be compelled to reveal facts which have come to his knowledge by reason of his profession, if by revealing such facts he will betray or risk to betraying the confidence which  a third person has placed in him for the very reason of his profession.
(2)    The person who has confided or disclosed such facts may ensure that they be not revealed by him in whom he has placed his confidence.
(3)    Nothing in this Article shall affect the provisions of Arts. 267 and 344 of the penal Code.
Art.25.- Funeral- 1. Will of deceased.
(1)    Every person having the capacity to make a will may prescribed the conditions of his funeral.
(2)    He may appoint one or more persons to ensure that such provisions are carried out.
(3)    The persons so appointed and, failing such, any other person who shows that he has a material or moral interest may apply to the court of the place of the death to enforce those provisions.
Art. 26.-2 Will not expressed.
(1)    Where the deceased has not expressed his will in the form mentioned in Art, 25, the conditions of his funeral shall be fixed by his surviving spouse or by his nearest relatives.
(2)    In default of the spouse and of relatives present or known at the time of the death, such conditions shall be fixed by the person who take the initiative thereof.
(3)    In case of contestation, the matter may be laid before the court of the place of death by the most diligent party.
Art.27- Image of the person,-1. Principle.
The photograph or the image of a person may not be exhibited in a public place of death by the most diligent party.
Art.28- 2. Exception.
The consent of the person concerned shall not be required where the reproduction of his image is justified by the notoriety of such person or by the public office which he occupied or by the requirements of justice or of the police or by a scientific, cultural or didactic interest, or where the reproduction of the image is made in connection with facts, events or ceremonies of public interest or which have taken place in public.
Art.29.-3. Sanction.
(1)    Where the image of a person is exhibited or offered for sale without the consent of such person, except in the cases referred to in Art. 28, such person may demand that the exhibition or offer for sale of his image be stopped.
(2)    The court may, if equity so demands, also award damages to such person with the limits of the enrichment derived by the person who made use of the image from its exhibition or offer for sale.
(3)    Damages for moral prejudice may be awarded if the exhibition or offer for sale does not cease immediately, when the cessation thereof is demanded.
Art.30.-4. Rights of the family.
(1)    Where the person whose image is exhibited or offered for sale is dead or not in a position to manifest his will, the right referred to in Art 29 shall vest in his relatives if the exhibition or offer for sale is of such a nature as to be prejudicial to the honor or reputation of the deceased person.
(2)    The only persons competent to represent the family for the application of the Article are the spouse, or, in his default, the nearest descendant or, in default of a descendant, the nearest ascendant of the person concerned.
(3)    In case of equal degrees, the eldest descendant or the oldest ascendant is the only person competent to represent the family.

Art. 31. – Inviolability of correspondence.
(1)    The addressee of a confidential letter may not divulge its contents without the consent of its author.
(2)    He may, however, produce it in judicial proceedings if he shows that he has a legitimate interest.</item>
        <item>TITLE II CAPACITY OF PERSONS
Chapter 1. General Principles
Art. 192.- Rule of capacity.
 
Every physical person is capable of performing all the acts of civil life unless he is declared incapable by the law.
 
Art. 193.- General disabilities.
 
General disabilities depend on the age or mental condition of persons or on sentences passed upon them.
 
Art. 194.- Special disabilities.
 
(1) Special disabilities may be prescribed by reason of the nationality of persons or of the functions exercised by them.
(2) They shall be as provided by Chapter 5 of this Title (Arts. 389-393) and by special laws.
 
Art. 195.- Voluntary restrictions.
 
(1) No person may renounce, even partially, the enjoyment or the exercise of civil rights.
(2) Any voluntary restriction imposed on the enjoyment or on the exercise of such rights shall be of no effect unless it is justified by a lawful interest.
 
Art. 196.- Proof of disability.
 
(1) Capacity is presumed.
(2) Any person who alleges the disability of a physical person shall prove that such person is under a disability.
 
Art. 197.- Bodies corporate and property with a specific destination.
 
The capacity of bodies corporate and property with a specific destination shall be regulated, according to their nature, by the provisions applicable to them,</item>
        <item>Title III. Companies and properties with different locations
Chapter 1. Administrative bodies and the Church
Art. 394.- Government.

(1) The State shall be held legally as a person.
(2) He can also hold and exercise all the rights that are compatible with his character.

Art. 395.- Division of regional territories.

(1) Provincial Governments, District Governments, District and Sub-district Governments and urban and rural communities have the right to have rights.
(2) Therefore, they can obtain and use all the rights granted by the administrative law through their respective bodies.
              Art. 396.- Ministers.

(1) Ministers of the Ethiopian government have rights.
(2) Therefore, they can obtain and use all the rights granted by the administrative law through their respective bodies.

Art. 397.- Public administration authorities and institutions.

All public administration officials, offices or institutions are subject to the rights conferred by administrative law, according to their profession.

Art. 398.- Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church.

(1) The Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church is considered as one person by law.
(2) Therefore, he can use all the rights given by administrative laws through his organs.

Art. 399.- Churches, parishes and monasteries.

Churches, congregations and monasteries that are part of the Ethiopian Orthodox Tewahedo Church have the same rights as all professions under the conditions and limits determined by the administrative law.
          Art. 400.- Powers and bodies.

(1) The authority of the bodies referred to in the above number and the authority of the bodies authorized to represent these bodies are stipulated by the administrative law.
(2) They may require these parties to observe certain conditions or procedures in order to exercise certain rights.

Art. 401.- Failure to meet statutory requirements.

(1) The actions of the bodies referred to in this chapter that exceed the powers given by law without fulfilling the formal conditions given by law shall have no effect.
(2) The provisions of sub-para. (1) It is applicable in these cases even if it is not clear in law.

Art. 402. - Rejection.

(1) Sec. 401 can be called by any interested party.
(2) It cannot be summoned after ten years have passed since the date of the act.

Art. 403.- Non-contractual liability.

(1) The entities described in this chapter shall be defined in accordance with the provisions of the title of this code, "Extracontractual Liability and Unlawful Enrichment" (Sec. 2027-2161).
(2) Pay any illegal enrichment received in accordance with the provisions of the corresponding title (sections, 2162-2178).</item>
        <item>Title V. Continued
Vacation time. 1. Substitute changes
Article 1. General provisions
Article 1.- The opening of the series and the creation of series items

Art. 826.- Series opening.
(1) that a person is dead; The decedent\'s estate is opened at the place where he had his principal residence at the time of his death.
. . . .

Art. 827.- Things that make up a will-1. Life insurance.

(1) Amounts payable under a life insurance contract to which the deceased was a party; If the deceased fails to appoint a beneficiary or if the insured becomes the beneficiary instead of the heirs of the deceased. Another indicator.
(2) They are not part of his inheritance in any other way.
          Art. 829.- Different types of success.

(1) The estate of a deceased person may be inherited or inherited.
(2) He may be disinherited partially; And part of it can be disinherited.
(3) The property not bequeathed by the deceased belongs to his legal heirs.

Article 2 Success ability
Art. 830.- Conditions for success.

A person cannot represent the deceased unless he or she survives and is eligible to succeed.

Art. 831. Life of deceased heir.

(1) The proof of the residence of the deceased on the date of his death is in accordance with the provisions of this title on "bodily bodies" (Article 47-153).
(2) Regarding the consequences of absence, the provisions of this ownership shall be applicable (Article 154-173).
(3) Nothing in this section shall affect the provisions relating to the participation of representatives.

Art. 832. - People who died at the same time.

When two or more people die and it is not possible to determine which of these people will survive the other, it is not possible to ensure that the succession of each of them will survive the other, the successor of these people will be governed as the successor.
             The last one left to accept anything from the other successors</item>
        <item> TITLE VI GENERAL GOODS AND GOODS
Chapter 1. General items
Section .1126. Various types of equipment.
All devices are portable or fixed.

Art. 1127.- Physical property.- 1. Principle.

Physical resources are things that have physical existence and can move themselves or be moved by people without losing their individual characteristics.

Section .1128.- 2. Mortgage securities.

Unless otherwise provided by law, claims and other intangible rights embodied in securities are considered tangible assets.

Art. 1129. 3. Forces of nature.

Unless otherwise provided by law, natural forces of economic value, such as electricity, are considered physical goods where they are occupied by humans.

Art. 1130.- Immovable objects.

The land and buildings are considered immovable.

Art. 1131.- Internal components of goods. 1. Instructions.

Unless otherwise specified, the material rights or relationships apply to all internal entities.

Art. 1132.- 2. Definition.

(1) Anything that is normally considered to be a part of something is considered an intrinsic part.
(2) Any substance that is physically integrated with the object and cannot be separated without destroying or damaging the object is considered to be an internal part of the object.

Art. 1133.- 3. Timber Corporation.

(1) Trees and associations must be part of the body until they are separated from the ground.
(2) Contracts for separation from the land or that imply separation shall be considered as a separate physical object.

Art. 1134.- 4. Rights of third parties.

(1) Anything moving or stationary in the body ceases to form a separate substance.
(2) All rights previously held by third parties are forfeited.
(3) Nothing shall affect the right of a third party to file a claim based on liability for damages or unjust enrichment.
     </item>
        <item> TITLE VII. Private ownership
Chapter 1. Acquisition, transfer, disposal and certificate of ownership
Section 1. Acquisition of ownership rights
Article 1. Work
Art. 1151.- Instructions.

A person who owns a physical property intends to own it.

Art. 1152.- Animals.

(1) Trained or captive animals that escape from their owner\'s control and do not try to recapture them within the next month, or stop trying to capture them for a month, shall be ownerless.
(2) The provisions referred to in sub-section (1) shall not apply to horses or asinine species or their breeding or to camels and cattle.

Art. 1153.- Livestock breeding.

(1) A swarm of bees that have left their hive is considered to have no master.
(2) The person who settled in the hive becomes the owner of this herd due to his ownership.
(3) The former investor may take them to the place of their eviction and immediately reach their residence.

Art. 1154.- Something found.- 1. To find duty.

(1) A person who acquires or possesses a physical object must comply with administrative regulations requiring him or her to report what he or she has found.
(ii) In the absence of these regulations, to inform the owner of the findings and to take all necessary steps to investigate the circumstances.

Art. 1155.- 2. Possession of material.

(1) The applicant has fulfilled the above obligations. 1154 holds what is found in his hand.
(2) take all reasonable steps to protect against such circumstances.</item>
        <item> TITLE VIII Church ownership, usufruct and other rights in RAM

Chapter 1. Joint ownership
Article 1. General provisions
Art. 1257.- Instructions.

(1) One thing may be owned by several persons.
(2) Nothing in Title IX of this Act shall affect regulations relating to agricultural associations and official associations of home owners. (Articles 1489-1534).

Art. 1258.- How to adjust joint ownership.

(1) Subject to the mandatory provisions of the law, the rights and obligations of the co-investors shall be subject to the goods generated by the co-investors and the contracts entered into by the co-investors.
(2) In the absence of the documents or agreements referred to in subsection, these provisions shall apply. (1) made or these documents or terms are defective or contrary to law;

Art. 1259.- Presumption of equity.

The shares held by each co-owner are assumed to be equal.

Art. 1260.- Rights on shares.

(1) Each shareholder may dispose of or reserve his shares.
(2) Creditors of each common investor may attach the shares.
Art. 1261.- Preemptive legal right.
(1) The common shareholders have the legal right to compel a third party to sell the shares obtained from the common property to them.
(2) The right in subsection 1 (1) shall be exercised in the manner prescribed in chapter 4 of this title (sections 1386-1409).

Art. 1262.- Issuance of shares.

(1) If a joint investor has surrendered his share in the common property, this share will be transferred to the other joint investors.
(2) A co-investor who has surrendered his shares shall be liable for the debts that existed before the surrender.

Art. 1263. Use of object.

Each co-owner may use the jointly owned property for the purpose for which it was acquired and taking into account the rights of the other co-owners.

Art. 1664. - Addition.

(1) The fruit of an object held in common is shared.
(2) Each co-investor may at any time apply for the distribution of such fruits.

Art. 1265.- Management of jointly owned objects-1. Majority rule.</item>
        <item>Title X. Registrants of Real Property
Chapter 1. Keeping records and notes
Art. 1553.- Instructions.

Real estate records are maintained by custodians of real estate records in each district guazat.

Art. 1554.- Organizing places to keep records.

(1) The appointment and rank of real estate registrars and their assistants shall be as prescribed by the Department of Agriculture.
(2) The Minister shall determine the material organization of the sites for the preservation of real estate records; They also ensure that their work is done correctly.
(3) Take reasonable steps to protect and preserve real estate records.

Art. 1555.- Land distribution districts.

(1) A real estate register shall be kept in each repository according to the districts in which the land is divided.
(2) The Ministry of Agriculture shall determine the boundaries of the districts in which the land is distributed.

Art. 1556.- Main register.

Property records and mortgage records are maintained for each ward and each district.

Art. 1557.- Registration of real estate.

If the conditions of the cadastre accept such a system, the real estate register must be kept in each district.

Art. 1558.- Register of owners.

If the cadastral area does not allow for the preparation of an immovable property register, the register of ownership shall be kept in each district.

Art. 1559.- Other records.

The Department of Agriculture may determine that additional records are to be maintained under a general directive or a directive that applies specifically to one or more conservation areas.

Art. 1560.- Records cannot be deleted.

The real estate register cannot be removed from the place where it is attached under any circumstances.

Art. 1561.- Notice of registration. -1 instructions.

Real estate registration is available to the public.

Art. 1562.- 2. Registration of real estate and owners.

(1) The custodians of records shall, upon request, provide certified true copies of the leaves included in the real estate records relating to the property.
(ii) Submits upon request a certified true copy of the leaf or leaves of an investor in the register of owners.
(3) When necessary, they must provide proof that the leaf of the immovable property does not have any registration or that there is no leaf regarding the registration of one owner.</item>
        <item>Administrative contracts
Chapter 1. General Provisions
Art. 3131 - Regulations applicable to contracts of administrative bodies.
(1) Contracts entered into by the government or other administrative authorities shall be governed by the provisions of this law on general contracts or special contracts.
(2) If the agreement is an administrative agreement, the provisions of this patent shall be in addition to or supersede these provisions.
Art. 3132 - Administrative agreements.
The agreement shall be considered as an administrative agreement:
(a) is expressly qualified as such by law or by the parties; Or
(b) related to public service activity if the party contracting with the administrative bodies implies permanent participation in the performance of this service; Or
(c) contains one or more provisions that can be motivated only by immediate consideration of the common good outside the relationship between individuals.
Art. 3133 - Application for certain businesses.
Businesses applying for government savings or offering their shares to the public may be asked by the competent authorities to comply with the procedures and systems prescribed by law by the regulatory bodies in completing their contracts.
Section 1. Contract
Article 1. License
Art. 3134 - accepted format.
(1) Unless otherwise provided by administrative laws or regulations, the contract summary of administrative authorities shall constitute a clear expression of interest on their part.
(2) In the absence of a formal provision, silence shall not be deemed to be a confirmation of an authority competent to ratify a contract.
(iii) The provisions of sub-para. (1) and (2) shall apply to the extension or modification of the contract.
Art. 3135 - General conditions applicable to management contracts. - 1. Draw a picture.
Model specifications, general clauses and general terms and conditions and instructions can be prepared by the administrators of each need </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="e2">
        <item>Preamble</item>
        <item>Preliminary</item>
        <item>BOOK I. JURISDICTION OF COURTS</item>
        <item>BOOK II. PARTIES TO SUITS</item>
        <item>BOOK III. GENERAL PROVISIONS  REGARDING CIVIL SUITS</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="de2">
        <item>Preamble
DECREE NO. 52 OF 1965
THE CIVIL PROCEDURE CODE DECREE
CONQUERING LION OF THE TRIBE OF JUDAH

HAILE SELASSIE I
ELECT OF GOD, EMPEROR OF EHTOPIA
 
WHEREAS it is desirable that further and better provisions be made regarding the administration of justice in civil matters:
NOW THEREFORE, in accordance with Article 92 of Our Revised Constitution and on the advice of Our Council of Ministers We hereby decree as follows:

1.    This Decree may be cited as “The Civil Procedure Code Decree, 1965”
2.    The Civil Procedure Code of 1965 shall be published in a separate volume appearing as Extraordinary Issue No. 3 1965 of the Negarit Gazeta.
3.    All rules, whether written or customary, previously in force concerning matters provided for in the Civil Procedure Code of 1965 shall be replaced by this Code and are hereby replaced. </item>
        <item>Preliminary
Art 1. Scope of application
(1)    The provisions of this Code shall apply from the day of its coming into force to all suits pending on such day and instituted thereafter.
(2)    Any suit pending on the coming into force of this Code shall be completed by the court having jurisdiction under the law repealed by this Code, notwithstanding that such court is not mentioned in the Code.
Art 2. Periods of time
(1)    Where periods of time have expired prior to the coming into force of this Code, noting in this Code shall revive them.
(2)    Where periods of time have been introduced by this Code, they shall run from the day of the coming into force of this Code,
(3)    Where periods of time have been extended by this Code, the periods provided for by this Code shall apply but the time having run prior to the coming into force of this Code shall be deducted.
(4)    Where periods of time have been shortened by this Code, the periods provided for by the law repealed by this Code shall continue to run on the coming into force of this Code.
Art 3. – Interpretation
In this Code, unless the context otherwise requires, the following terms and expressions shall have the following meaning:
“affidavit” shall mean a statement of facts in writing lawfully sworn or affirmed:
“Court” shall mean a court established by law:
“decree” shall mean the formal expression of any preliminary or final adjudication which, so far as concerns the court expressing it, conclusively determines the lights of the parties concerning all or any of the matters in dispute in the suit,
“decree- holder” shall mean any person in whose favor a decree has been passed or an order capable of execution has been made and shall include the transferee of a decree:
“execution officer” shall mean any judge, officer of any court of any other person appointed by the Minister of Justice to execute decrees,
“foreign court” shall mean a court situate outside Ethiopia,                                            ,
“foreign judgment” shall mean the judgment of a foreign court:
“government pleader” shall include:
a)    any officer appointed by the government to perform all or any of the functions imposed by this Code on the government pleader: and
b)    any pleader acting under the directions of the government pleader,
“judgment” shall mean the statement given by a court of the grounds of a decree or order:
“judgment- debtor” shall mean any person against whom a decree has been passed or an order capable of execution has been made;
“law” shall include proclamations, decrees, orders and any subsidiary legislation made there under,
“legal representative” shall mean any person who in law represents a person under disability or the estate of a deceased person;
“mesne profits” of property shall mean those profits which the person in wrongful possession of such property  actually received or might with ordinary diligence have received therefrom, together with interest on such profits, but shall not include profits due to improvements made by such person;
“order” shall mean the formal expression of any decision of a court which is not a decree;
“person under disability”  mean any person who is not capable under the law;
“pleader”  shall mean any an advocate and shall include any person entitled to appear and plead for another;
“prescribed” shall mean prescribed  by regulations under this Code; “registrar” shall mean the registrar or assistant registrar or a court and shall include any clerk of court assigned by the registrar  to carry out all or part of the duties of a registrar:
“share in a corporation” shall be deemed to include stock, debenture stock, debentures or bonds. </item>
        <item>BOOK I. JURISDICTION OF COURTS

CHAPTER 1. GENERAL PROVISIONS
 
Art 4- Courts to try suits unless barred

With out prejudice to the provisions of the following Articles, the  courts shall have jurisdiction to try all civil suits other than those of which their cognizance is expressly nor impliedly barred.
Art 5- Res judicata
(1)    No court shall try any suit or issue in which the matter directly and substantially in issue has been directly and substantially in issue in a former suit between the same parties, or between parties under whom they or any of them claim, litigating under the same title, and has been heard any finally decided.
(2)    Any matter which might and ought to have been made a ground of defense or attack in the former suit shall be deemed to have been directly and substantially in issue in such suit.
(3)    Any relief claimed in the former suit which has not been expressly granted by the decree passed in such suit shall, for the purposes of the Article, be deemed to have been refused.
(4)    Where persons litigate in good faith in respect of public or private rights claimed in common for themselves and others, all persons interested in such right shall, for the purposes of this Article, be deemed to claim under the persons so litigating.
Art.6- Review of judgments
(1)    Notwithstanding the provisions of Art.5, any party considering himself aggrieved by a decree or order from which an appeal lies, but from which no appeal has been preferred, or by a decree or order from which no appeal lies, may, on payment of the prescribed court fee, apply for a review of judgment to the court which gave it where:
(a) subsequently to the judgment, he discovers new and important matter, such as forgery, perjury or bribery. Which after the exercise of due diligence, was not within his knowledge at the time of the giving of the judgment: and
(b) had such matter been known at the time of the giving of the judgment, it would have  affected the substance of the decree or order the review of which is sought.
(2) An application for review shall contain the same particulars
as a memorandum of appeal and shall be supported by an affidavit  containing strict proof of the fulfillment of the conditions laid down in sub-art. (1) (a). The application shall be filed within one month of the ground of application having been discovered by the applicant.
(3) On granting the application, after giving notice to the opposite party to enable him to appear and be heard in support of the decree or order  the review of which is sought, the court shall make such order in regard to the re-hearing of the case as it thinks fit.
(4) No appeal shall be lie from any decision of the court granting or rejecting an application for review.
Art 7.- Priority
(1)    One and the same civil suit may not be instituted in more than one civil court.
(2)    Where a suit may be instituted in any one of several courts, the court in which the statement of claim was first filed shall have jurisdiction and the suit shall pending in such court.
Art. 8- Pendency
(1)    No court shall try any suit in which the matter in issue is also directly and substantially in issue in a previously instituted civil suit between the same parties, or between parties under whom they or any of them claim, litigating under the same title, where such civil suit is pending in the same or any other court in Ethiopia having jurisdiction to grant the relief claimed.
(2)    The pendency of a suit in a foreign court shall not preclude the courts in Ethiopia from trying a suit founded on the same cause of action.
(3)    Where the matter in issue in a suit pending in another court or is so closely connected with a suit pending in another court that it can not properly the tried separately the provisions of Arts. 11 or 244 and  245, as the case may be, shall apply.
Art. 9- Want of material jurisdiction
(1)    A statement of claim field in a court not having material jurisdiction shall be rejected in accordance with Art. 231.
(2)    When and as soon as a court is aware  that  it has  not material jurisdiction to try a suit, it shall proceed in accordance with Art. 245 notwithstanding that no objection is taken under Art. 244 to its material jurisdiction.
Art. 10- Want of local jurisdiction
(1)    A statement of claim field in a court not having local jurisdiction shall be rejected in accordance with Art. 231.
Provided that a court which has jurisdiction under Arts. 19-30 may not reject a statement of claim on the ground that another court also has local jurisdiction.
(2)    Any objection taken under Art. 244 to the local jurisdiction of a court shall be finally decided by the said court and no order made, judgment given or decree passed  by the said court may be invalidated  unless such an objection was taken and the decision thereon has caused a failure of justice.
Art. 11-  Consolidation of suits
(1)    Where two or more suits or appeals are pending between the same parties in the same court, in which the same or similar questions of law or fact are involved, the court may, of its own motion or on the application of either party, order a consolidation of such suits or appeals on such terms as it thinks fit.
(2)    Where two or more suits are pending between the same parties in different courts, in which the same or similar questions of law or fact are involved, or where two or more suits pending between the same parties indifferent court are so closely connected that they can not properly be tried separately, either party may, at any time before evidence is taken in any of such courts, apply for an order that such suits be consolidated.
(3)    An application under sub-art. (2) shall be made to the High Court, where the suits are pending in courts which are all subordinate thereto, or to the Supreme Court, where one or more of the courts in which the suits are pending is a division of the High Court on circuit.
(4)    The court to which the application is made shall, on granting the same, direct by which of the subordinate courts the suit shall be tried.
(5)    The provisions of sub-arts. (2)-(4) shall also apply where two or more appeals, in which the same or similar questions of law of fact are involved, are pending between the same parties is difference courts of the same grade.</item>
        <item> BOOK II. PARTIES TO SUITS
 
Art. 32- Scope of application

(1)    The provisions of the Book shall apply in any proceeding under this Code.
(2)    In applying the provisions of this Book to appeals, to so far as may be, the word “plaintiff” shall be held to include an appellant, the word “defendant” a respondent, and the word “suit” an appeal.
CHAPTER 1. GENERAL PROVISIONS
 
Art. 33 - Qualifications

(1)    Any person capable under the law may be a party to a suit.
(2)    No person may be a plaintiff unless he has a vested interest in the subject-matter of the suit.
(3)    No person may be a defendant unless the plaintiff alleges some claim against him.

Art. 34- Representation

(1)    A person under disability may sue or be sued through his legal representative.
(2)    Where a person under disability is not represented by his legal representative, the proceedings shall be stayed until a legal representative is appointed in  accordance with the relevant provisions of the Civil Code.
(3)    Without prejudice to the provisions of the following Articles, bodies corporate may be represented in accordance with the relevant provisions of the Civil or Commercial Code, as the case may be.
(4)    Representation in maritime matters shall be as provided for by the Maritime Code.
(5)    In all suits concerning property administered by a trustee, executor or administrator,  where the contention is between the persons beneficially interested in such property and a third  person, the trustee, executer or administrator shall represent the persons so interested, and it shall not be necessary to make them parties to the suit unless the court otherwise directs.

Art. 35- Joinder o f  plaintiffs

All persons in whom any right to relief in respect of or arising from the same transaction or series of transactions is alleged to exist, whether jointly, severally or in the alternative, may be joined in one action as plaintiffs where, is such persons borough separate actins any common question of law or fact would arise.

Art. 36- Joinder of defendants

(1) All persons against whom the right to any relief is alleged to exist, whether jointly, severally or in the alternative, may be joined as defendants where. If separate suits were brought against such person, any common question of law or fact would arise.
(2)    The plaintiff may join as parties to the same suit all or any of the persons severally, or jointly and severally, liable on the same contract, including parties to negotiable instruments.
(3)    Where a suit concerns property administered by several trustees, executors or administrators, all such persons shall be made parties to a suit against one or more of them, provided that trustees, executors or administrators outside Ethiopia need not be made parties unless otherwise ordered by the court on an application being made under Art 43.
(4)    Where the plaintiff sues for the recovery of immovable property free of occupants, such occupants, whatever their title, shall all be made parties to the suit.
(5)    Where the plaintiff is in doubt as to the person from whom he is entitled to redress, he may join two or more defendants so that the question as to which, if any, of the defendants is liable, and so what extent, may be determined as between all the parties.
(6)    It shall not be necessary that every defendant be interested as to all the relief claimed in any suit against him.

Art. 37- Judgment for or against one or more parties judgment may be given:

(a)    for such one or more of the plaintiffs as may be found to be entitled to relief, for such relief as he or they may be entitled to;
(b)    against such one or more of the defendants as may be found to be liable, according to their respective liabilities.

Art. 38- Representative party

(1)    Where several persons have the same interest in a suit, one or more of such persons may sue or be sued or may be authorized by the court to defend on behalf or for the benefit of all persons so interested on satisfying the court that all persons so interested agree to be so represented.
(2)    Any person on whose behalf or for whose benefits a suit is instituted or defended under sub-art. (1) may apply to the court to be made a party to such suit.
Art 39.- Misjoinder and nonjoinder
(1)    No suit shall be defeated by reason only of the misjoinder or nonjoinder of parties and the court may in every suit deal with the matter in dispute so far as regards the rights and interest of the parties actually before it.
(2)    Any objection on the ground of misijoinder or nonjoindr of parties shall be raised at the earliest possible opportunity and any objection not so raised shall be deemed to have been waived.

 Art.40.- Substitution or addition of parties

(1)    W here a suit has been institute in the name of a wrong person as plaintiff  or it is doubtful whether it has been instituted in the name of the right plaintiff, the court, on being satisfied that the suit has been instituted though a bona fide mistake and that it is necessary for the determination of the real matter in dispute so to do, may at any time order that any other person be substituted or added as plaintiff on such terms as it shall fix.
(2)    The court may at any time, of its own motion or on the application of either party and on such terms as it shall fix, order that the name of any party improperly joined as plaintiff or defendant be struck out and that there be added the name of any person who ought to have been joined as plaintiff or defendant or whose presence is necessary for the determination of all the questions involved in the suit:
Provided that no person shall be added as plaintiff without him consent.
(3)    Where a defendant is added, the statement of claim shall, unless the court otherwise directs, be amended accordingly and a copy thereof shall thereupon be served on the new defendant and, if the court thinks fit, on the original defendant.
(4)    Nothing in this Article shall prevent a third party at any time before judgment from substituting himself for either party with the consent of such party on showing that he is qualified under the provisions of Art. 33.
(5)    Where it appears to the court at the hearing of an appeal that any person who was a party to the suit in the court from whose decree the appeal is preferred, but who has not been made a party to the appeal, is interested in the result of the appeal, the court may adjourn the hearing and direct that such person be made a respondent.

Art. 41.- Intervention of third party

(1)    Any person interested in a suit between other parties may intervene therein at any time before judgment.
(2)    The intervention shall be made by the filing of a separate statement containing all the grounds which justify such person in intervening.
(3)    Where the intervention is allowed, the proceedings shall be stayed until the parties have been served with a copy of the statement of the intervening party.
(4)    Where service is not effected for a reason attributable to the intervening party, he shall be deemed to have withdrawn his statement.
(5)    Nothing in this Article shall affect the provisions of Arts. 293-299.

Art. 42.- Intervention of public prosecutor

The public prosecutor shall intervene whenever his intervention is required by law, in particular in cases relating to:
(a)    civil status (Arts. 116, 122 and 156 Civil Code);
(b)    incapacity (Arts. 234,254 and 377 Civil Code);
(c)    marriage (Arts. 592, 608, 609 and 612 Civil Code);
(d)    bankruptcy (Arts. 975, 978, 980, 1004 and 1017 Commercial Code).

Art. 43- Joinder of third party

(1)    Where a defendant claims to be entitled to contribution or indemnity from any person not a party to the suit, he may in his statement of defense show cause why the third party is liable to make contribution or indemnity and the extent of such liability and apply to the court for an order that such person be made a party to the suit.
(2)    Where the application is allowed, the third party shall be served with a copy of the statement of claim and defense and, upon being summoned to appear on such day as the court shall fix, shall be deemed to be in the same position as a defendant.
(3)    The claim as between the defendant and the third party shall be tried in such manner as the court shall direct.
(4)     The provisions of this Article shall apply by analogy where a defendant claims to be entitled to contribution or indemnity from any other defendant in the suit:
Provided that nothing in this sub-article shall prejudice the plaintiff against any defendant in the suit.

Art. 44- Suing partners in name of firm

Two or more persons claiming or being liable as partners and carrying on business in Ethiopia may sue or be sued in the name of the firm, if any, of which such persons were partners at the time of the accruing of the cause of action, and any party to a suit may in such case apply to the court for a statement of the names and addresses of the persons who were at the said time partners in such firm, to be furnished and verified in such manner as the court may direct.

Art. 45- Disclosure of partners names

(1)    Where a suit is instituted by partners in the name of their firm, the plaintiffs or their pleader shall, on demand in writing by or on behalf of any defendant, forthwith declare in writing the names and place of residence of all the persons constituting the firm on whose behalf the suit is instituted.
(2)     Where the plaintiffs or their pleader fail to comply with any demand made under sub-art.(1), all proceedings in the suit may, upon an application for that purposes, be stayed upon such terms as the court may direct.
(3)    Where the names of the partners are declared in accordance with sub-art. (1), the suit shall proceed in the same manner, and the same consequences in all respects shall follow, as if they had been named as plaintiffs in the statement of claim:
Provided that all the proceedings shall nevertheless continue in the name of the firm

Art. 46.- Suing person carrying on business in name other than his own.

Any person carrying on business in a name or style other than his own name may be sued in such name or style as if it were a firm name and any provision in this Code which applies to suits by or against firms and persons carrying on business in a name other than their own shall apply so far as the nature of the case will permit.

Art. 47.- Suits between co-partners

Any provision in this Code which applies to suits by or against firms and persons carrying on business in a name other than their own shall apply to suits between a firm and one or more of the partners therein and to suits between firms having one or more partners in common.  </item>
        <item>BOOK III. GENERAL PROVISIONS  REGARDING CIVIL SUITS
 
Art. 79- Scope of application

(1)    The provisions of this Book shall, so far as may be, apply in any proceedings under this Code.
(2)    In applying the provisions of this Book to appeals, so far as may be, the word “plaintiff” shall be held to include an appellant, the word “defendant” a respondent and the word “suit” an appeal.
CHAPTER 1. PLEADINGS
 
Art. 80- Contents of pleading

(1)    Pleading shall mean a statement of claim, statement of defence, counter-claim, memorandum of appeal, application or petition and any other document originating proceedings or field in replay thereto.
(2)    Every pleading shall be written in ink, printed or typewritten on the prescribed paper and shall contain and contain, only a statement in a concise form of the material facts on which the party relies for his claim or defense and shall be in a form as near as may be to the appropriate Form in the First Schedule to this Code.
(3)    Whenever particulars may be necessary beyond those mentioned in the said appropriate Form, such particulars shall be stated in the pleading, with dates and items if necessary.
(4)    Sums and numbers shall be expressed in words and figures and where a sum is expressed in foreign currency, its equivalent in Ethiopian currency shall be indicated.
(5)    Dates shown in the Gregorian or other calendar shall also indicated in the Ethiopian calendar.

Art. 81- Condition precedent

Any condition precedent, the performance of occurrence of which is intended to be contested, shall be distinctly specified and, subject thereto, an averment of the performance or occurrence of all conditions precedent necessary for the case of the plaintiff or defendant shall be implied in his pleading.

Art. 82- New fact

The plaintiff or defendant, as the case maybe, shall raise by his pleading all matters which show the action counter-claim not to be maintainable, or that the transaction is either void or avoidable in point of law, and all such grounds of defense or reply, as the case maybe, as if not raided would be likely to take the opposite party by surprise or would raise issues of fact not arising out of the preceding pleadings.

Art. 83- Denial to be specific

If shall not be sufficient for a defendant in his statement of defense to deny  generally the grounds alleged by the statement of claim of for a plaintiff in his reply to a counter-claim to deny generally the grounds alleged by the defendant and each party shall deal specifically with each allegation of fact of which he does not admit the truth except damages.

Art. 84- Denial of contract

Where a contract is alleged in any pleading, a bare denial of the same by the opposite party shall be construed only as a denial in fact of such contract or of the matters of fact from which the same may be implied, and not as a denial of the  legality or sufficiency in law of such contract.

Art. 85- Effect of document to be stated

Whenever the contents of any document are material, it shall be sufficient in any pleading to state the effect thereof without setting  out the whole or any part hereof, unless the precise words of the document or any part thereof are material.

Art. 86- Condition of mind

Whenever it is material to allege malice, fraudulent intention, knowledge or other condition of the mind of any person, it shall be sufficient to allege the same as a fact without setting out the circumstances from which thee same may be inferred.

Art. 87- Notice

Whenever it is material to allege notice to any person of any fact matter or thing, it shall be sufficient to allege such notice as a fact, unless the form or the precise terms of such notice, or the circumstances from which such notice may be inferred, are material.

Art. 88- Implied contract or relation

(1)    Whenever any contract or relation between any persons may be implied from circumstance, it shall be, sufficient to allege such contract or relation as a fact  and to refer generally to such circumstances without setting them out in detail.
(2)    Where a person pleading as provided in sub-art. (1) wishes to reply in the alternative on more contracts or relations than one as to be implied from such circumstances are referred to , he may state the same in the alternative.

Art. 89- Legal presumptions

Neither party need in any pleading allege any matter of fact which the law presumes in his favour or as to which the burden of proof lies up on the other party, unless the same has first been specifically denied.

Art. 90- Departure

No pleading shall, except by way of amendment, raise any new ground of claim or contain any allegation of fact inconsistent with the pervious pleadings of the party pleading the same.

Art. 91- Amendment of pleading

(1)    The court may at any time before judgment allow either party to alter or amend his pleading in such manner and on such terms as to costs or otherwise as may be just, and all such amendment shall be made as may be necessary for the purpose of determining the real questions in dispute.
(2)    Where a party who has obtained leave to amend fails to amend within the time fixed by the court, he shall not be permitted to amend thereafter, unless the time is extended by the court.
(3)    A further and better statement of the nature of the claim or defense, or further and better particulars of any matter stated in any pleading may in all cases be ordered by the court of its own motion or on the application of either party upon such terms, as to costs or otherwise, as may be just.
(4) The court may at any time order to be struck out or amended in any pleading any matter which is unnecessary or scandalous or which may tend to prejudice, embarrass or delay the fair trial of the suit.
(5) Where pleadings are so amended as to have the effect of brining the claim within the jurisdiction of a higher court, the court in which the suit was instituted shall transfer the claim to such higher court for trial.

Art. 92- Verification of pleading

(1)    Unless otherwise expressly provided by law, every pleading shall be verified at the foot by the party or by one of the parties pleading or by some other person other than the pleader, directly acquainted with the facts of the case.
(2)    In suits by or against a corporation, any pleading may be signed and certified on behalf of the corporation by the secretary or by any director or other officer of the corporation who is able to depose to the facts of the case.
(3)    In suits by or against the Government, any pleading shall be signed by such person as the Government may, by general or special order, appoint in this behalf, and shall be verified by any person whom the Government may so appoint and who is acquainted with the facts of the case.
(4)    Where persons sue or are sued as partners in the name of their firm under Art. 44, it shall suffice that nay pleading basined or verified by any one of such person.

Art. 93- Pleading to be signed

Every pleading shall be signed by the party or his pleader, if any, or where a party is for good cause unable to sing, by any other person duly authorized by him to sing the same or to sue or defend on his behalf.</item>

    </string-array>
    <string-array name="e3">
        <item>PREFACE TO THE CRIMINAL CODE</item>
        <item>BOOK I CRIMES AND CRIMINALS</item>
        <item>TITLE II THE CRIME AND ITS COMMISSION</item>
        <item>TITLE III CONDITIONS OF LIABILITY TO PUNISHMENT IN RESPECT OF CRIMES</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="de3">
        <item>PREFACE TO THE CRIMINAL CODE
It is nearly half a century since the 1957 penal code entered into operation. During this period, radical political, economic and social changes have taken place in Ethiopia. Among the major changes are the recognition by the Constitution and international agreements ratified by Ethiopia of the equality between religions nations, nationalities and peoples, the democratic rights and freedoms of citizens and residents, human rights, and most of all, the rights of social groups like women and children. After all these phenomena have taken place, it would be inappropriate to allow the continuance of the enforcement of the 1949 Penal Code.
Another discernible gap in the Penal Code is its failure to properly address crimes born of advances in technology and the complexities of modern life. The Penal Code does not incorporate crimes such as the hijacking of aircraft, computer crimes and money laundering. Besides, as regards crimes related to corruption and drugs although they are nowadays, attracting attention both in legislation and follow-up not only within national frontiers but also on the regional and international levels, due to the grave crises they are causing, the Penal code does not adequately deal with such crimes with the degree of seriousness they deserve.
Another point that should not be overlooked is the Penal Code’s failure to acknowledge the grave injuries and sufferings caused to women and children by reason of harmful traditional practices. Surely, the Constitution guarantees respect for the cultures of peoples, but it does not buttress up those practices scientifically proven to be harmful. It is also futile to issue a law that does not have the trust and support of the people for is usually remains impracticable. But it is well recognized in the philosophy of criminal legislation that the legislature should, by adopting progressive laws at times, educated and guide the public to dissociate itself from harmful traditional practices.
Furthermore, it is desirable to adopt a comprehensive code by assembling the various criminal provisions published in the Negarit Gazeta in a disintegrated manner. Similarly, since the parallel application, of the regular Penal Code and the Revised Special Penal Code in respect of similar matters disregards equality among citizens, the existence of a comprehensive Criminal Code will put an end to such practice.
In order to eliminate the above-mentioned shortcomings and adopt a comprehensive Criminal code, substantial activities have been undertaken throughout the entire Country. Discussions have been held on the draft criminal Code prepared by the Ministry of Justice and the Justice and Legal System Research Institute. Legal and medical professionals, psychiatrists, different institutions of higher education and professional associations have made significant contributions through the opinions they gave to the enactment of the law. Representatives of the people selected from different sectors and associations have forwarded important views in discussion forums on the draft laws conducted in Addis Ababa and the regions. It is mainly on the basis of public opinion that punishments have increased in respect of crimes like rape and aggravated theft. Moreover, the opinions of legal scholars and the laws and experiences of foreign countries have been consulted to enrich the content of the Criminal Code.
Finally, one point that must not be left unmentioned is the matter concerning the determination of sentence. Since it is essential to facilitate the method by which Courts can pass similar punishments on similar cases, some major changes have been made in the provisions of the Code. Provisions of the Penal Code that used to make sentencing complicated and difficult have been amended. Provisions have been inserted which enable the Courts to pass the appropriate penalty for each case by carefully examining from the lightest to the most severe punishment. A sentencing manual will also be issued to ensure and control the correctness and uniformity of sentencing.
Another point which must be raised in connection with the determination of sentence is that the purpose of Criminal law is to preserve the peace and security of society. It protects society by preventing the commission of crimes, and a major means of preventing the commission of crime is punishment.
Punishment can deter wrongdoers from committing other crimes; it can also serve as a warning to prospective wrongdoers. Although imprisonment and death are enforced in respect of certain crimes the main objective is temporarily or permanently to prevent wrongdoers from committing further crimes against society. And in such cases with the exception of the death sentence even criminals sentenced to life imprisonment can be released on parole before serving the whole term; in certain crimes convicts can be released on probation without the pronouncement of sentence or without the enforcement of the sentence pronounced. This helps wrongdoers to lead a peaceful life and it indicates the major place which the Criminal Law has allocated for their rehabilitation.
The fact that wrongdoers, instead of being mad to suffer while in prison, take vocational training and participate in academic education, which would benefit them upon their release, reaffirms the great concern envisaged by the Criminal Code about the reform of criminals.
It must be noted that, by laying down in the Code express provisions concerning these cases, it is intended that Courts should, on passing sentence, take into account the purpose of the law and the different aims of punishment.
It is hoped that this Criminal Code, which has been revised through all these persistent efforts, will ensure respect for the order, peace and security of the State and its peoples as well as respect for the rights and freedoms of its citizens and inhabitants.
Being convinced that this Code will enable to accelerate the economic progress of the State, that is will strengthen a steady order of free market and that it will, above all, contribute towards the promotion of a fair judicial system, in our country, pursuant to Article 55 (1) of the Constitution of the Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia it is hereby proclaimed as follows:
1.    Short Title:
This Proclamation may be cited as “The Criminal Code of the Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia 2004.”
2.    Repeal:
The following proclamations:
a)    the Penal Code of the Empire of Ethiopia 1957, and
b)    the Revised Special Penal Code of the provisional Military. Administration Council 1982, Proclamation No. 214/1982, are hereby repealed as from the 9th of May, 2005.
3.    Special Case:
As provided in Article 3 of this Code, nothing shall affect the application of special laws and regulations.
4.    Effective Date:
This Criminal Code as published in separated volume of the Federal Negarit Gazeta under proclamation No. 414/2004, shall come into force as of the 9th of May 2005.</item>
        <item>BOOK I CRIMES AND CRIMINALS
TITLE I CRIMINAL LAW AND ITS SCOPE
CHAPTER I SCOPE OF THE LAW
Article 1- Object and Purpose
The purpose of the criminal code of the Federal Democratic Republic of Ethiopia is to ensure order, peace and the security of the State, its peoples, and inhabitants for the public good.
It aims at the prevention of crimes by giving due notice of the crimes and penalties prescribed by law and should this be ineffective by providing for the punishment of criminals in order to deter them from committing another crime and make them a lesson to others, or by providing for their reform and measures to prevent the commission of further crimes.
 
Article 2- Principle of Legality.
(1) Criminal law specifies the various crimes, and the penalties and measures applicable to criminals.
(2) The Court may not treat as a crime and punish any act or omission which is not prohibited by law.
The Court may not imposed penalties or measures other than those prescribed by law.
(3) The Court may not create crimes by analogy.
(4) The above provisions shall not prevent the Court from interpreting the law. In cases of doubt the Court shall interpret the law according to its spirit, in accordance with the meaning intended by the legislature so as to achieve the purpose it has in view.
(5) Nobody shall be tried or punished again for the same crime for which he has been already convicted, punished or subjected to other measures or acquitted by a final decision in accordance with the law.
 
Article 3- Other Penal Legislation.
Nothing in this code shall affect regulations and special laws of a criminal nature:
Provided that the general principles embodied in this Code are applicable to those regulations and laws except as otherwise expressly provided therein.
 
Article 4- Equality Before the Law.
Criminal law applies to all alike without discrimination as regards persons, social conditions, race, nations, nationality, social origin, colour, sex, language, religion, political or other opinion, property, birth or other status.
No difference in treatment of criminals may be made except as provided by this Code, which are derived from immunities sanctioned by public international and constitutional law, or relate to the gravity of the crime or the degree of guilt, the age, circumstances or special personal characteristics of the criminal, and the social danger which he represents. </item>
           <item>TITLE II THE CRIME AND ITS COMMISSION
CHAPTER I THE CRIME
Article 23- Crimes.
(1)    A crime is an act which is prohibited and made punishable by law.
In this Code, an act consists of the commission of what is prohibited or the omission of what is prescribed by law.
(2)    A crime is only completed when all its legal, material and moral ingredients are present.
(3)    Notwithstanding the provision of sub-article (2) of this Article, a juridical person shall be criminally liable to punishment under the conditions laid down in Article 34 of this Code.
(4)    A crime is punishable where the Court has found the crime proved and deserving of punishment.
Article 24 – Relationship of Cause and Effect.
(1)    In all cases where the commission of a crime requires the achievement of a given result, the crime shall not be deemed to have been committed unless the result achieved is the consequence of the act or omission with which the accused person is charged.
This relationship of cause and effect shall be presumed to exist when the act within the provisions of the law would, in the normal course of things, produce the result charged.
(2)    Where there are preceding, concurrent or intervening causes, whether due to the act of a third party or to a natural or fortuitous event, which are extraneous to the act of the accused, this relationship of cause and effect shall cease to exist when the extraneous cause in itself produced the result.
If, in such a case, the act with which the accused person is charged in itself constitutes a crime he shall be liable to the punishment specified for such a crime.
(3)    Relationship of cause and effect shall be presumed to exist between each cause specified under sub-article (2) above and the result achieved, when the result is the cumulative effect of these causes, even though each cause cannot independently produce the result.
Article 25- Place and Time of the Crime.
(1)    A crime is committed at the place where and at the time when the criminal performed or failed to perform the act penalized by criminal law.
An attempt is committed at the place where and at the time when the criminal performed or failed to perform the preliminary acts which constitute such an attempt.
(2)    With regard to non-instantaneous crimes where the act and the criminal result do not coincide the crime is deemed to have been committed both at the place of the unlawful act and that of its result.
Similarly, an attempt is deemed to have been committed both at the place where the criminal attempted the crime and the place he intended the result to be produced.
For purposes of prosecution, the jurisdiction of the place where the result was achieved is subsidiary to that of the place of commission.
(3)    When a combination or repetition of criminal acts is an element of an ordinary or aggravated crime as provided under Article 61, or when the act is pursued over a period of time, the place where and the time when the crime is committed shall be the place where and the time when one of the combined or repeated acts or part of the acts pursued is committed. </item>
        <item>TITLE III CONDITIONS OF LIABILITY TO PUNISHMENT IN RESPECT OF CRIMES
CHAPTER I CRIMINAL RESPONSIBILITY

Section 1- Ordinary Responsibility

Article 48- Criminal Responsibility and Irresponsibility.
(1) The criminal who is responsible for his acts is alone liable to punishment under the provisions of criminal law.
(2) A person is not responsible for his acts under the law when, owing to age, illness, abnormal delay in his development, deterioration of his mental faculties, one of the causes specified under Article 49sub-article 1 or any other similar biological cause, he was incapable at the time of his act, of understanding the nature or consequences of his act, or of regulating his conduct according to such understanding.
(3) The Court may order in respect of an irresponsible person such suitable measures of treatment or protection as are provided by law (Arts. 129-131).

Article 49- Partial Responsibility.
(1) He who owing to one of the causes specified under Article 48 sub-article (2) above, or a derangement or an abnormal or deficient condition or any other similar biological cause was, at the time of his act, partially incapable of understanding the nature or consequences thereof or regulating his conduct according to such understanding shall be partially liable to the punishment specified for the crime committed. The court shall determine the sentence in accordance with Article 180.
(2) In addition to a penalty the Court may order such appropriate measures of treatment, correction or protection as are provided by law (Arts. 129-131).

Article 50- Crimes Committed in a State of Irresponsibility Caused by Intoxication or Other Similar Conditions.
(1) The provisions excluding or reducing liability to punishment shall not apply to any person who, in order to commit a crime or knowing that he could commit a crime, intentionally put himself into a condition of absolute irresponsibility or of limited responsibility by means of alcohol or drugs or any other means.
The general provisions of this Code are applicable in such a case.
(2) If a criminal by his own fault has put himself into a condition of absolute irresponsibility or of limited responsibility while he was aware, or could or should have been aware, that he was exposing himself, in such a condition, to the risk of committing a crime, he shall be tried and punished under the ordinary provisions governing negligence, if the crime committed is punishable on such a charge (Art. 59).
(3) In the case of a crime which was neither contemplated nor intended and was committed in a state of absolute irresponsibility into which the criminal put himself by his own fault, the provision of Article 491 of the Special Part of this Code relating to crimes against public safety shall apply.
(4) No person shall be liable to punishment where he commits a crime while in a state of absolute irresponsibility, into which he has been coerced or for which he has no fault on his part.

Article 51- Expert Examination in Doubtful Cases.
(1) When there is a doubt as to the responsibility of the accused person, whether absolute or partial, the Court shall obtain expert evidence and may order an enquiry to be made as to the character, antecedents and circumstances of the accused person.
Such evidence shall be obtained particularly when the accused person shows signs of a deranged mind or epilepsy is deaf and dumb or is suffering from chronic intoxication due to alcohol or due to drugs.
(2) The expert or experts shall be appointed by the Court under the ordinary rules of procedure. The Court shall define their terms of reference and the matters to be elucidated.
The expert evidence shall describe the present condition of the accused person and its effect upon his faculties of judgment and free determination. It shall, in addition, afford guidance to the Court as to the expediency and the nature of medical treatment of safety measures.
(3) On the basis of the expert evidence the Court shall make such decision as it thinks fit. In reaching its decision it shall be bound solely by definite scientific findings and not by the appreciation of the expert as to the legal inferences to be drawn there from.

Section II- Infants and Juvenile Delinquents

Article 52- Infancy: Exoneration from Criminal Provisions.
Infants who have not attained the age of nine years shall not be deemed to be criminally responsible. The provisions of this Code shall not apply to them.
Where a crime is committed by an infant, appropriate step may be taken by the family, school or guardianship authority.

Article 53- Special Provisions Applicable to Young Persons.
(1) Where a crime is committed by young persons between the ages of nine and fifteen years, the penalties and measures to be imposed by the courts shall be only those provided in Articles 157-168 of this Code.
Young persons shall not be subject to the ordinary penalties applicable to adults nor shall they be kept in custody with adult criminals.
(2) The provisions of Articles 158-168 of this Code shall not apply unless the criminal is convicted.
However, where the young person is irresponsible, the provisions of Articles 129-133 shall apply.

Article 54- Expert Evidence and Enquiry.
(1) For the purpose of assessing sentence the Court may require information about the conduct, education, position and circumstances of the young criminal. It may examine his parents as well as the representatives of the school, guardianship authorities and the institutions concerned.
The Court may require from the above-mentioned persons and institutions the production of any files, particulars, medical and social reports in their possession concerning the young person and his family.
(2) The Court before passing penalties or measures may order the young criminal to be kept under observation in a medical or educational centre, a home or any other suitable institution.
The Court may require the production of expert evidence regarding the physical and mental condition of the young person. The Court shall put such questions as may be necessary to any expert for the purpose of informing itself as to the physical and mental state of the young person and inquire what treatment and measures of an educational, corrective or protective kind would be most suitable.
(3) In reaching its decision the Court shall be bound solely by definite scientific findings and not by the appreciation of the expert as to the legal inferences to be drawn.

Article 55- Assessment of Sentence.
In assessing the penalties or measures the Court shall take into account the age, character, degree of mental and moral development of the young criminal, as well as the educational value of the penalties or measures to be applied.
The Court may vary its order whenever it is of the opinion that this will help to achieve better results (Art. 164).

Article 56- Criminals over Fifteen but Under Eighteen years of Age.
(1) If at the time of the commission of the crime the criminal was over fifteen by under eighteen years of age, he shall be tried under the ordinary provisions of this Code.
(2) The Court may, in assessing sentence, take into account the circumstances of the case, in particular the age of the criminal, his incorrigible or dangerous disposion and the likelihood of his reform either by applying the general provisions regarding ordinary mitigation of penalties (Art. 179) or by applying one of the special penalties specified for young persons (Arts. 166-168).

CHAPTER II CRIMINAL GUILT
Section I- Intention, Negligence and Accident.

Article 57- Principle; Criminal Fault and Accident.
(1) No one can be punished for a crime unless he has been found guilty thereof under the law.
A person is guilty if, being responsible for his acts, he commits a crime either intentionally or by negligence.
(2) No one can be convicted under criminal law for an act penalized by the law if it was performed or occurred without there being any guilt on his part, or was caused by force majeure, or occurred by accident.

Sub-Section I- Guilt in Case of a Simple Crime

Article 58- Criminal Intention
(1) A person is deemed to have committed a crime intentionally where:
(a) he performs an unlawful and punishable act with full knowledge and intent in order to achieve a given result; or
(b) he being aware that his act may cause illegal and punishable consequences, commits the act regardless that such consequences may follow.
(2) An intentional crime is always punishable save in cases of justification of excuse expressly provided by law (Arts. 68-81).
(3) No person shall be convicted for what he neither knew of or intended, nor for what goes beyond what he intended either directly or as a possibility, subject to the provisions governing negligence.

Article 59- Criminal Negligence.
(1) A person is deemed to have committed a criminal act negligently where he acts:
(a) by imprudence or in disregard of the possible consequences of his act while he was aware that his act may cause illegal and punishable consequences; or
(b) by a criminal lack of foresight or without consideration while he should or could have been aware that his act may cause illegal and punishable consequences.
A Person is guilty of criminal negligence when, having regard to his personal circumstances, particularly to his age, experience, education, occupation and rank, he fails to take such precautions as might reasonably be expected in the circumstances of the case.
(2) Crimes committed by negligence are liable to punishment only if the law so expressly provides by reason of their nature, gravity or the danger they constitute to society.
The Court shall assess sentence according to the degree of guilt and the dangerous character of the criminal, and according to his realization of the possible consequences of his act or his failure to appreciate such consequences as he ought to have done.

Sub-section II- Criminal Guilt in Case of Concurrence and Recidivism

Article 60- Concurrent Crimes.
A person commits concurrent crimes:
a) In cases of material concurrence, when the criminal successively commits two or more similar or different crimes, whatever their nature; or
b) in cases of notional concurrence, when the same criminal act simultaneously contravenes several criminal provisions or results in crimes with various material consequences; or
c) in the case of a criminal act which, though flowing from the same criminal intention or negligence and violating the same criminal provision, causes the same harm against the rights or interests of more than one person.

Article 61- Unity of Guilt and Penalty.
(1) The same criminal act or a combination of criminal acts against the same legally protected right flowing from a single criminal intention or negligence, cannot be punished under two or more concurrent provisions of the same nature if one legal provision fully covers the criminal acts.
(2) Successive or repeated acts against the same legally protected right flowing from the same initial criminal intention or negligence constitute one crime; the criminal shall be punished for the said crime and not for each of the successive acts which constitute it.
Similarly, where the repetition or succession of criminal acts or the habitual or professional nature of a crime constitutes an element of an ordinary or aggravated crime, or where the criminal act is pursued over a period of time, the criminal shall be regarded as having committed a single crime and not concurrent material crimes.
(3) In cases where the criminal is regarded to have intention to commit a specific crime, in particular where he committed a crime on property to obtain unlawful enrichment or he made counterfeit currency, used it or put it into circulation or executed a forged document and used it, the subsequent acts performed by the criminal himself after the commission of the main crime for the purpose of carrying out his initial criminal scheme shall not constitute a fresh crime liable to punishment and are merged by the unity of intention and purpose.

Article 62- Renewal of Guilt Entailing a Fresh Penalty.
When a criminal having committed a crime as specified in Article 61 commits with renewed criminal intention or negligence another crime of the same kind, whether against the same person or the same legally protected right, such crime constitutes a fresh crime and the Court shall aggravate the sentence on ground of concurrence as provided in Article 184.

Article 63- Guilt in Case of Related Crimes.
When a criminal commits a crime with the intention or causing or facilitating the commission of another punishable crime the provisions regarding aggravation of penalty in case of concurrence shall apply (Art. 184), when this has been attempted unless such crime is declared by law to be an aggravated crime.

Article 64- Guilt in Case of Other Concurrent Material Crimes.
Where a criminal successively commits different crimes other than those specified in Article 62 and 63, the provisions of Article 184 of this Code shall apply.
Article 65- Gilt in Case of Notional Concurrence Violating Different Legal Provisions.
In case of notional concurrence where the act simultaneously contravenes different legal provisions, the punishment shall be determined in accordance with Article 187(1).
Article 66- Guilt in Case of Notional Concurrence Resulting in Crimes with Various Material Consequences.
(1) When a given crime implying an injury to persons or property, or the use of arms, instruments or dangerous means, fire or explosives, poison or toxic substances, entails and injury whereby the elements constituting a second crime have materialized, whether it be bodily injury, injury to health, death of a human being or the destruction of another person’s property, the Court shall apply the following principles for determining the guilt and the penalty:
(a) if the result achieved was intended or foreseen and accepted by the criminal (Art. 58(1)), when he committed the first crime, he shall be punished for both the first crime and the resulting crime and aggravation shall apply in accordance with the relevant provisions (Arts. 184 and 187(2)(a)), due regard being had to the combination of the elements constituting the two intentional crimes;
(b) if an intentional crime results in a crime committed by negligence (Art. 59(1)) there shall be concurrence between the intentional act and the resulting crime due to negligence, and the Court shall increase the penalty accordingly (Art. 187(2)(a));
(c) if the first crime committed by negligence results in another crime punishable for negligence, there shall be concurrence between the crimes committed by negligence and the Court shall aggravate the penalty accordingly (Art. 187(2)(b)).
(d) Aggravation shall apply in particular where the criminal result was achieved by means endangering public safety, such as arson, explosion, use of explosives or where communication or public health are in danger as well as in the case of exposure of persons, maltreatment, brawl, abortion, rape or sexual outrages (Arts. 187(2)(c) and 184).

Article 67- Guilt in Case of Recidivism.
The Court shall aggravate the penalty on ground of recidivism (Art. 188) when a fresh intentional crime the minimum penalty of which is six months of simple imprisonment has been committed within five years of serving a sentence of imprisonment in whole or in part of having been remitted by pardon.

Section II- Lawful Acts, Justifiable Acts and Excuses
Sub-section I- Lawful Acts

Article 68- Acts Required or Authorized by Law.
Acts required or authorized by law do not constitute a crime and are not punishable; in particular:
(a) acts in respect of public, State or military duties done within the limits permitted by law;
(b) acts reasonably done in exercising the right of correction or discipline; or
(c) acts done in the exercise of private rights recognized by law, where the conditions and limits of the exercise of such rights are not exceeded.

Article 69- Professional Duty.
An act done in the exercise of a professional duty is not liable to punishment when it is in accordance with the accepted practice of the profession and the doer does not commit any grave professional fault.

Sub-section II- Justifiable Acts and Excuses
  </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="e4">
        <item>PREFACE </item>
        <item>Preliminary</item>
        <item>BOOK I.TRADERS AND BUSINESSES</item>
        <item>BOOK II. Prosecution and Inquiry</item>
        <item>BOOK III. Preliminary Inquiry and Committal for Trial</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="de4">
        <item>PREFACE
CONQUERING LION OF THE TRIBE OF JUDAH
HAILE SELASSIE I
ELECT OF GOD, EMPEROR OF ETHIOPIA
In the Modern world, no nation can hope to expand its commercial and economic life unless there exists a firm legal basis which will assure the necessary elements of stability and security in business transactions while at the same time providing a sufficiently articulated yet flexible framework within which trade and commerce may flourish and grow. Today, in Ethiopia, the development of commerce has out grown the provisions of the laws relating to business organizations and bankruptcy which were promulgated during the first years of Our Reign and which were adapted to the commerce and industry of those early days. The Commercial life of Ethiopia has expanded, increasing numbers of Ethiopian and foreign companies have been formed and registered, and more complex methods of transacting business have been developed in recent years.
Recognizing the impetus which a modern Code regulating the constitution and activities of all business organisations could give to the further growth of trade and commerce, We directed the Codification Commission created by US to prepare a modern Commercial Code which would serve for the present day as well as provide a solid foundation for the further refinement of laws treating of these subjects. We have directed that in the expansion and consolidation of Our commercial laws, great attention should be given to the control of all trading, and in particular to the control of the carriage of passengers and goods, an aspect of commercial activity which has increased greatly in the last decade. Similarly, in view of the further expansion of both foreign and internal commerce, it has been necessary to elaborate laws governing negotiable instruments and banking transactions.
The Commercial Code which is today being promulgated fulfils these requirements. It is grounded in Ethiopia’s ancient laws and customs and has been further extended by reference to the laws of other great commercial powers. We are confident that this Code will fulfil the aspirations of Our Beloved People and will assist in the swift and orderly development of Ethiopia’s economic life. Our parliament has studied with care and patience the detailed provisions of this Code and what has been approved by it is well suited to the needs of Our Own Country and to those persons and enterprises from other lands who are participating and sharing in the benefits of the commercial life of our Empire. We are ever mindful that in the all-important task of the codification of Our laws We have been guided by Almighty God, and that the fruits of this work will underline the principle of international justice without which no nation can survive or prosper. </item>
        <item>PROCLAMATION No. 166 of 1960
THE COMMERCIAL CODE PROCLAMATION OF 1960
CONQUERING LION OF THE TRIBE OF JUDAH HAILE SELASSIE I
ELECT OF GOD, EMPEROR OF ETHIOPIA
WHEREAS the progress of Our Empire in the field of commerce requires the codification of Our commercial laws; and
WHEREAS a Commercial Code has been prepared under Our supervision and has received the approval of Our Senate and Chamber of Deputies;
 NOW, THEREFORE, in accordance with Articles 34 and 88 of Our Revised Constitution, We approve the resolutions of Our Senate and Chamber of Deputies and We hereby proclaim as follows:
1.    This Proclamation may be cited as the “Commercial Code Proclamation, 1960.”
2.    The Commercial Code of 1960, as published in a separate volume appearing as Extraordinary Issue No. 3 of 1960 of the Negarit Gazeta, shall come into force on the  11th day of September, 1960.
3.    The Bankruptcy Law and the Company law of 12th July, 1933, are hereby repealed as from the 11th day of September, 1960. </item>
        <item>BOOK I.
TRADERS AND BUSINESSES

TITLE I. GENERAL PROVISIONS APPLICABLE TO TRADERS
 
Chapter 1. Provisions Applying to Persons Carrying on a Trade

Art. 1. - Scope of application of the Civil Code.

Unless otherwise provided in this Code, the provisions of the Civil Code shall apply to the status and activities of persons and business organisations carrying on a trade.

Art. 2. - Scope of application of the Maritime Code.

    The relevant provisions of the Maritime Code shall apply to persons and business organisations carrying on maritime trade

Art. 3. - Persons and business organisations.

The provisions of this Code applicable to persons other than those provisions applicable to physical persons only shall apply to business organisations.
 Nothing shall affect the special provisions of Book II and Book V Title IV of this Code applicable to business organisations only.

Art. 4. - Bodies corporate under Public Law.

1.    Unless otherwise expressly provided by law, bodies corporate under public law, such as administrative or religious institutions or any other public undertakings shall not be deemed to be traders even where they carry on activities under Art. 5.
2.    The provisions of sub-art. (1) shall not apply to undertakings in which bodies corporate under public law only participate.

Chapter 2. Traders

Art. 5. - Persons to be regarded as traders.
Persons who professionally and for gain carry on any of the following activities shall be deemed to be traders:
1.    Purchase of movables or immovable with a view to re-selling them either as they are          
       or after alteration or adaptation;
2.    Purchase of movables with a view to letting them for hire;
3.    Warehousing activities as defined in Art. 2806 of the Civil Code:
4.    Exploitation of mines, including prospecting for and working of mineral oils;
5.    Exploitation of quarries not by handicraftsmen;
6.    Exploitation of salt pans;
7.    Conversion and adaptation of chattels, such as foodstuffs, raw materials or semi-  
      finished products not by handicraftsmen;
8.    Building, repairing, maintaining, cleaning, painting or dyeing movables not by  
      handicraftsmen;
9.    Embanking, levelling, trenching or draining carried out for a third party not by  
      handicraftsmen;
10. Carriage of goods or persons not by handicraftsmen;
11. Printing and engraving and works connected with photography or cinematography
      not by handicraftsmen.
12. Capturing, distributing and supplying water;
13. Producing, distributing and supplying electricity, gas, compressed air including  
     heating and cooling;
14. Operating places of entertainment or radio or television stations;
15. Operating hotels, restaurants, bars, cafes, inns, hairdressing establishments not  
     operated by handicraftsmen and public baths;
16.    Publishing in whatever form, and in particular by means of printing,engraving,
     photography or recording;
17.   Operating news and information services;
18.   Operating travel and publicity agencies;
19.   Operating business as an agent, broker, stock broker or commercial agent;
20.   Operating a banking and money changing business;
21.   Operating an insurance business.

Art. 6. - Agricultural or Forestry undertakings.

1.    Persons who carry on activities relating to agriculture, forestry, breeding cattle or maintaining pastureland, shall not be deemed to be traders where they sell the products of the land they exploit or use, or animals or the products of animals bred mainly from the resources of the land which the said persons exploit or use.
2.    Such persons shall not be deemed to be traders whether the exploitation is individual or collective, such as an agricultural community or a cooperative undertaking.
3.    Nurserymen who sell plants which grow on the land they exploit or use shall not be deemed to be traders.

Art. 7. - Agricultural Products How Dealt with.

1.    Persons who carry on activities under Art. 6 (1) shall not be deemed to be traders where they deal with their products in accordance with the usual practice of their business, so long as such dealing relates only to products of the land which they exploit or use, or to animals or products of animals bred mainly from the resources of the land which they exploit or use.
2.    Such persons shall not be deemed to be traders whether the undertaking is individual or collective such as an agricultural community or a cooperative undertaking.


Art. 8. - Fishermen and persons breeding fish, shell-fish or shells.
 Fishermen and persons who breed fish or shell-fish or shells shall not be deemed to be traders where they sell the products of their fishing or breeding.

Art. 9. - Handicraftsmen.
1.   The provisions of this Code relating to traders shall not apply to handicraftsmen.
2.   Handicraftsmen are persons who carry on an independent activity, who live mainly  
      on their own manual work, who may carry on their activity with the assistance of      
      members of their family and of not more than three employees or apprentices and  
      who buy such material only as is necessary for carrying out their activities, without    
      setting up stocks.
3.    Handicraftsmen may use mechanical power.
4.    Handicraftsmen are subject to the provision of any special law relating to their  
       activities.

Art. 10. - Business Organisations.
1.    Business organisations shall be deemed to be of a commercial nature where their  
       objects under the memorandum of association or in fact are to carry on any of the  
       activities specified in Art. 5 of this Code.
2.    Share companies and private limited companies shall always be deemed to be of a  
       commercial nature whatever their objects.

Chapter 3. Persons Capable of Carrying on a Trade
Art. 11. - Persons incapable under the Civil Code
1.    Persons incapable under the Civil Code may not carry on any trade.
2.    Where incapable persons carry on a trade, they shall not, subject to the provisions of Art. 14 and 15, acquire the status of traders and their acts may be invalidated in accordance with the relevant provisions of the Civil Code.

Art. 12. - Tutors.
    Tutors may not carry on a trade in the name and on behalf of a minor except in the     cases provided in Art. 288 of the Civil Code. The same provisions shall apply to the tutor of an interdicted person.

Art. 13. - Emancipated Minors.
1.    Notwithstanding the provisions of Art. 333 of the Civil Code,emancipated minors may not carry on a trade unless authorised in writing by the family council.
2.    In default of authorisation under sub-art. (1), emancipated minors shall not be deemed to be of age.

Art. 14. -Effect of Minority in relation to third parties.
Notwithstanding the provisions of Art. 318 of the Civil Code, where a minor who carries on a trade has caused himself to be entered in the commercial register as though he were of age, his being a minor shall not affect third parties, in accordance with Art. 121 of this Code.

Art. 15. - Publication of incapacity.
Where a person has been declared incapable, such incapacity shall not affect third parties     unless notice of such incapacity has been entered in the commercial register (Art. 121).

Chapter 4. Carrying on a Trade by Married Persons

Art. 16. - Married persons may carry on trade.
Any married person may carry on a trade as though he were unmarried unless his spouse objects thereto as provided in Art. 645 of the Civil Code.

Art. 17. - Notification of objection.
1.    As between spouses an objection under Art. 16 may be notified to the trading spouse in any manner.
2.    An objection under Art. 16 shall not affect third parties, in accordance with Art. 121 of this Code, unless notice of such objection has been entered in the commercial register.

Art. 18. - Setting aside of objection.
1.    Where the trading spouse is of the opinion that the objection is not justified, having regard to the interest of the family, he may apply to the family arbitrators to set aside the objection.
2.    Where the objection is set aside by the arbitrators, a notice to this effect shall be entered in the commercial register.

Art. 19. - Debts contracted by the trading spouse.
    Debts contracted by the trading spouse shall be deemed to be debts of the marriage within the meaning of Art. 659 of the Civil Code and may be recovered on the     personal estate of each spouse and on common property.

Art. 20. - Effect of objection.
Where an objection under Art. 16 has been entered in the commercial register, debts contracted by the trading spouse may be recovered on his personal estate only.

Art. 21. - Cooperation of spouses.
    Where spouses together carry on a trade, they shall both be deemed to be     traders, unless it is shown that one of them is the employee of the other.

Chapter 5. Right to Act as a Trader
Art. 22. - Freedom to carry on trade.
    Subject to such prohibitions or lawful restrictions regarding unfair competition as may be prescribed, any person or business organization has the right to carry on any trade in accordance with the provisions regulating such trade.

Art. 23. - Legal prohibitions or restrictions.
1.    Particular persons may be restricted or prevented from acting as traders or from carrying on a particular trade by legal provisions setting up prohibitions or incompatibilities.
2.    Specific requirements as to age, qualifications, sex, nationality or license may be
      imposed by law in respect of particular trades.

Art. 24. - Effect of prohibitions and restrictions.
1.    Persons who carry on a trade subject to prohibition or restriction or without having
      the prescribed qualifications shall be liable to the penalties provided by law.
2.    Persons who carry on a trade subject to prohibition or restriction may not invoke
      the said prohibition or restriction to free themselves from liabilities incurred in carrying    
      on a trade subject to prohibition or restriction. They may not hold themselves out to
      be traders to third parties but they shall be liable as though they were traders.

Art. 25. - Associations.
1.    Associations may not carry on any trade.
2.    Any violation of the provisions of sub-art. (1) shall constitute a ground for dissolution
       under Art. 461 of the Civil Code.

Art. 26. - Business organisations carring on trade
    No business organisation shall carry on a trade which it is not permitted to carry on or
   which is subject to specific requirements with which the said business organisation has
   not complied.

Art. 27. - Bodies corporate under Public Law.
    The cases where a trade may be carried on by administrative or religious institutions or any other public undertaking and the conditions and effect of such trade shall be prescribed. </item>
        <item>BOOK II. BUSINESS ORGANISATIONS

TITLE I. GENERAL PROVISIONS
 
Art. 210. - Business organisation defined.

1.    A business organisation is any association arising out of a partnership agreement.
2.    Any business organisation other than a joint venture shall be deemed to be a legal person.

Art. 211. - Partnership  agreement.

    A partnership agreement is a. contract whereby two or more persons who intend to join together and to cooperate undertake to bring together contributions for the purpose of carrying out activities of an economics nature and of participating in the profits and losses arising out thereof, if any.

Art. 212. - Different business organisations.

1.    There are six forms of business organisations under this Code:
a.    ordinary partnership;
b.    joint venture;
c.    general partnership;
d.    limited Partnership;
e.    share company;
f.    private limited company;

2.    Special provisions applicable to cooperative organisations may be prescribed.

Art. 213. - Commercial business organisations.

1.    Any business organisation other than an ordinary partnership may be a commercial business organisation within the meaning of Art. 10 (1) of this Code.
2.    Where a commercial business organisation is created in the form of an ordinary partnership or where the form of the organisation is not specified, the commercial business organisation shall be deemed to be a general partnership.

Art. 214. - Formation to be in writing.

    The formation of any business organisation other than a joint venture shall be of no effect unless it is made in writing.

Art. 215. -Vow provisions.

1.    Any provision giving all the profits to one partner shall be of no effect.
2.    Any provision relieving one 01 more of the partners of his share in the losses shall be of no effect.

Art. 216 - Agents.

1.    A business organisation shall acquire rights and incur liabilities by its agents in accordance with the provisions relating to agency.
2.    A business organisation shall act in legal proceedings by its agents.
3.    Any summons to be served on a business organisation shall be served at the head-office.

Art. 217. - Dissolution under the law or by agreement.

    Any business organisation shall be dissolved:
a.    where its purpose has been achieved or cannot be achieved;
b.    where the partner agree to dissolution prior to the expiry of the term for which the busine!18organisation was formed;
c.    where the term for which the business organisation was formed expires, unless the partners agree to continue the business organisation.

Art. 218. - Dissolution by the court.

1.    Notwithstanding any provision to the contrary, a business organisation may be dissolved for good cause by the court on the application of a partner.
2.    There shall be good cause in particular where a partner seriously fails in his duties or becomes through infirmity or permanent illness or for any other reason incapable of carrying out his duties or where disagreement exists between the partner.

Art. 219. - Publicity.

1.    Any business organisation other than a joint venture sha11 be made known to third parties.
2.    Such publicity shall be made:
a.    by a notice published in a newspaper empowered to publish legal notices; and
b.    by the deposit of two copies of the documents provided: in Art. 221 with the official in charge of the commercial register; and
c.    by registration in the commercial register.

Art. 220. - Publication of notice.

    A notice under Art. 219 (2) (a) shall be published in a newspaper empowered to publish legal notices circulating at the place where the heed-office is situate.

Art. 221. –Deposit of documents

1.    A deposit under Art. 219 (2 (b) shall be made with the official in charge of the commercial register at the place where the head-office is situate.
2.    Two copies of the memorandum and all complementary documents, if any, shall be deposited.
3.    The official shall keep one copy of the documents deposited and shall send the second copy to the Department of the central commercial register provided in Art. 90 of this Code.
4.    Any person may, on payment of the prescribed fee, require the official in charge of a local or of the central commercial register to deliver to him a copy of all entries relating to a business organisation.

Art. 222. - Registration.

1.    The application for registration in the commercial register shall be deposited with the documents specified in Art. 221.
2.    The provisions of Art. 95-99 of this Code shall apply. The official in charge of the register shall examine whether the legal conditions relating to the formation of the business organisation have been fulfilled.

Art. 223. - Effect of publicity.

A business organization shall have no legal existence nor personality until all the provisions of this Code relating to publicity have been complied with and registration is published in accordance with Art. 87 of this Code.

Art. 224. - Modifications.

1.    Any modification in the memorandum of association shall be deposited.
2.    Any modification of a fact published and registered, shall be published and the entry shall be corrected in accordance with Art. 108 of this Code.

Art. 225. - Branches.

1.    Where a business organization comprises branches or agencies situate in places other than the place where the head-office is situate, the provisions of this Code relating to publicity shall be complied with in each place where a branch or agency is situate.
2.    Registration in the commercial register shall be made by way of summary registration and shall refer to the principal registration.
3.    A summary registration shall contain the same particulars as a principal registration and shall show the address of the branch and the name of the manager of the branch.

Art. 226. - Cancellation of registration.

    Where a business organisation is dissolved and wound-up, the liquidators shall apply for the registration of the business organisation in the commercial register to be cancelled. The business organisation shall have no legal personality after cancellation has been published in the Official Commercial Gazette. </item>
        <item>BOOK II
Prosecution and Inquiry
 
TITLE I
Setting in Motion Prosecution and Inquiry
Chapter 1 Setting justice in motion
 
Section 1 Accusation and complaint
 
Art. 11 __ Accusation in general.
 
(1) Any person has the right to report any offence, whether or not he has witnessed the commission of the offence, with a view to criminal proceedings being instituted.
(2) There shall be a duty to report in the cases provided in Art. 267,344 and 438 penal code.
 
Art. 12.___ Anonymous accusations.
 
Anonymous accusations which disclose serious beaches of the law and are on the face of them circumstantial and credible shall be investigated by the competent police authorities in the manner prescribed by Art. 22 et seq. with a view to ascertaining the truth or otherwise of the accusation.
 
Art. 13__ Offences punishable on complaint.
 
In the case of offences which under the law may be prosecuted and punished only upon a formal complaint by the injured party or those deriving rights from him, the provisions of Art. 217-222 and 721 Penal Code shall apply.
 
Art. 14 __ form of accusation or complaint.
 
(1) Any accusation (Art. 11) or complaint ( Art. 13) shall be reduced to writing by the person to whom it is mad and when completed shall be read over to the complainant who shall sign and date it.
(2) Where an accusation or complaint is made by more than one person ( Art.219 Penal Cade), all such persons shall sign it.
 
Art. 15 __ Accusation or complaint against an unknown offender.
 
Where the offender cannot be identified because he is unknown to the person making the accusation or complaint, such person shall furnish such details as are known to him with a view to establishing the identity of the offender.
 
Art. 16 __ Authority competent for receiving accusation or complaint.
 
(1) Any accusation (Art. 11) or complaint(Art. 13) may be made to the police or the public prosecutor. An accusation or complaint regarding a young person shall be made in accordance with Art. 172.
(2) Where it is made to the public prosecutor, the prosecutor shall forward it to the competent police officer with a view to an investigation being made under Art. 22 et seq.
 
Art. 17. __ Accusation or complaint addressed to wrong authority.
 
Where an accusation or complaint is made to a person or authority other than the police or the public prosecutor or to a police authority or a prosecutor having no jurisdiction, such person, authority or prosecutor shall without delay forward the accusation or complaint to the appropriate police authority or public prosecutor.
 
Art. 18.__ False accusation or Complaint.
 
Whosoever makes a false accusation or false complaint shall be liable to the punishments laid down in art. 441 and 580 Penal Code.
 
  </item>
        <item>BOOK III
 
Preliminary Inquiry and Committal for Trial
 
Art.80.—Principle.
 
(1) Where any person is accused of an offence under Art. 522 (homicide in the first degree) or Art. 637 (aggravated robbery) a preliminary inquiry shall be held under the provisions of this Book.
Provided that nothing in this Article shall prevent the High Court from dispending with the holding of a preliminary inquiry where it is satisfied by the public prosecutor that the trial can be held immediately.
(2) Where any person is accused of any other offence triable only by the High Court no preliminary inquiry shall be held unless the public prosecutor under Art. 38 (b) so directs.
(3) The provisions of this Book shall not apply to offences coming within the jurisdiction of the High Court which have been committed by young persons.
 
Art.81.—Court having jurisdiction.
 
(1) Without prejudice to the provisions of Art. 99-107, the preliminary shall be held before the Woreda Guezat Court within whose area of jurisdiction the offence was committed.
 
Art.82.—Procedure.
 
(1) All preliminary inquiries shall be held in the manner provided by the following Articles.
(2) An adjournment may be granted on the conditions laid down in Art. 94.
 
Art.83.—Opening of preliminary inquiry.
 
(1) Where the public prosecutor decides under Art. 80 (2) that a preliminary inquiry shall be held, he shall send a copy of his decision to the Woreda Guezat Court having jurisdiction and, where appropriate, to the public prosecutor acting before such court.
(2) The court shall fix the day on which the inquiry shall be held and cause to be summoned such witnesses as the prosecutor may wish to call in support of the prosecution.
(3) The case for the prosecution shall be conducted by the public prosecutor acting before the committing court.
 
Art.84.—Taking evidence for prosecution.
 
(1) Where the accused person appears or is brought before it, the court shall require the prosecutor to open his case and to call his witnesses.
 
Art.85.—Accused asked whether he wishes to make a statement.
 
(1) After the witnesses for the prosecution have been heard and their evidence recorded, the court shall ask the accused whether he wishes to make a statement in answer to the charge.
(2) He shall be informed that the preliminary inquiry does not constitute a trial and that the decision as to his guilt or innocence will be taken by the High Court and not by the committing court.
(3) He shall be informed that he is not bound to say anything but that any statement he may wish to make will be taken down in writing and may be put in at his trial.
 
Art.86.—Statement of accused.
 
(1) If the accused elects to make no statement, he shall forthwith be committed for trial before the High Court.
(2) If the accused elects to make a statement, such statement shall be taken down in writing, read over to him, signed by the accused and kept in the file.
 
Art.87.—Additional witnesses.
 
The court may at any time call any witness whose testimony it thinks necessary in the interests of justice, notwithstanding that the prosecutor has not applied for such witness to be summoned.
 
Art.88.—Recording of evidence.
 
Evidence shall be recorded in accordance with Art. 147 and the evidence of each witness shall be recorded on separate sheets of paper.
 
Art.89.—Committal for trial.
 
(1) After the statement, if any, of the accused has been taken down, the court shall commit the accused for trial before the High Court without specifying the charge or charges on which he is committed for trial.
(2) Such charge or charges shall be specified in the charge framed by the public prosecutor in accordance with Art. 109-122 of this Code.
(3) The court shall then require the accused to give a list of the witnesses he wishes to call at his trial together with their addresses.
 
Art.90.—Bond of witnesses.
 
(1) All witnesses who have given evidence at the preliminary inquiry shall execute before the committing court bonds binding themselves to be in attendance before such court and on such date as they shall be summoned to appear.
(2) Any witness who refuses to execute the bond may be kept in custody until the trial or until he binds himself.
 
Art.91.—Record to be forwarded to registrar.
 
(1) When the accused is committed for trial, the committing court shall send the original record and the exhibits (if any) to the registrar of the High Court. Any exhibit which from its bulk or otherwise cannot conveniently be forwarded to the registrar of the High Court may remain in the custody of the police.
(2) A list of all exhibits showing which of them are forwarded with the record and which remain in the custody of the police shall be sent to the registrar of the High Court with the record.
(3) The registrar of the High Court shall be responsible for making copies of the record and sending one to the public prosecutor and one to the accused.
 
Art.92.—Contents of record.
 
(1) The record shall contain the following particulars:-
(a) The serial number of the case; and
(b) The date of the commission of the offence; and
(c) The date of the accusation, if any; and
(d) The name and address of the accuser, if any; and
(e) The name, address occupation and age, if known, and nationality of the accused; and
(f) The offence shown and, where appropriation, the value of the property in respect of which or the special status of the person against whom the offence was committed; and
(g) The date of the warrant of arrest, if any, or on which the accused was first arrested; and
(h) The date on which the accused was first brought before a court; and
(i) The name of the prosecutor and, where appropriate, of the advocate for the defense; and
(j) The date of and reasons for any adjournment that may have been granted; and
(k) The date on which the preliminary inquiry was completed; and
(l) All statements made in the course of the preliminary inquiry, including those which may have been made by the accused; and
(m) the list of defense witnesses.
 
(2) The same particulars shall appear in the copy of the proceedings sent to the public prosecutor and the accused.
 
Art.93.—Accused may be remanded.
 
Without prejudice to the provisions of this Code relating to release on ball the committing court may order that the accused be kept on remand until the trial.
 </item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="e5">
        <item>ምዕራፍ 1</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 3</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 4</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="de5">
        <item>chapter1 details under [odstiuon 5</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="e6">
        <item>ምዕራፍ 1</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 3</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 4</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="de6">
        <item>chapter1 details</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="e7">
        <item>ምዕራፍ 1</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 3</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 4</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="de7">
        <item>ምዕራፍ details</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="e8">
        <item>ምዕራፍ 1</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 2</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 3</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 4</item>
        <item>ምዕራፍ 5</item>
    </string-array>
    <string-array name="de8">
        <item>chapter1 details under the last one admistration</item>
        <item>chapter2 details </item>
        <item>chapter </item>
        <item>chapter4  </item>
        <item>chapter5 details </item>
    </string-array>
</resources>